<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The law and the Gospell reconciled. Or the euangelicall fayth, and the morall law how they stand together in the state of grace A treatise shewing the perpetuall vse of the morall law vnder the Gospell to beleeuers; in answere to a letter written by an antinomian to a faithfull Christian. Also how the morality of the 4th Commandement is continued in the Lords day, proued the Christian Sabbath by diuine institution. A briefe catalogue of the antinomian doctrines. By Henry Burton.</title>
            <author>Burton, Henry, 1578-1648.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1631</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 169 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 58 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17305</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4152</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106965</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842671</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842671</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7347</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17305)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7347)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 563:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The law and the Gospell reconciled. Or the euangelicall fayth, and the morall law how they stand together in the state of grace A treatise shewing the perpetuall vse of the morall law vnder the Gospell to beleeuers; in answere to a letter written by an antinomian to a faithfull Christian. Also how the morality of the 4th Commandement is continued in the Lords day, proued the Christian Sabbath by diuine institution. A briefe catalogue of the antinomian doctrines. By Henry Burton.</title>
                  <author>Burton, Henry, 1578-1648.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 70 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I. N[orton] for Thomas Slatter, and are to bee sould at his shoppe in Blackfryars,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1631.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The Gospell and the law reconciled.</note>
                  <note>A variant of the edition with imprint ".. I.N. for Timothy Clardue".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Antinomianism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7347:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE LAW AND the Goſpell reconciled. <hi>OR</hi> The Euangelicall Fayth, and the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Law how they ſtand together in the ſtate of grace.</p>
            <p>A treatiſe ſhewing the perpetuall vſe of the Morall Law vnder the Goſpell to belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers; in anſwere to a letter written by an Antinomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a faithfull Chriſtian. Alſo how the mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> of the 4th Commandement is continued in the Lords day, proued the Chriſtian Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath by diuine inſtitution.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>fe Catalogue of the Antinomian doctrinoc. By HENRY BVRTON.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 TIM. 1.5.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The end of the Commandement is charity out of a pure heart, &amp; of a good conſcience, and of fayth vnfained.</p>
               <p>Vt Rota intra rotam currit: ſic lex intra Gratiam, et obſeruantia legis intra diuin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> curriculum miſericordiae eſt. <bibl>
                     <hi>Ambros.</hi> de <hi>Iacob,</hi> &amp;c, li. <hi>2.</hi> cap: <hi>11.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. N.</hi> for <hi>Thomas Slatter,</hi> and are to bee ſould at his ſhoppe in <hi>Blackfryars.</hi> 1631.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:7347:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7347:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HIGH and Mighty Prince, <hi>Charles,</hi> by the grace of God, King of Great <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Fayth, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ratious Soueraine, this ſmall treatiſe humbly pleades your Royall Patronage by a double title: the one, from the Author of it, your old ſeruant, who oweth all he is to your Maieſty; the other, from the worke it ſelfe, being a defence of the Morall Law of God againſt the <hi>Antinomian Libertines</hi> in theſe daies, who deny to beleeuers any more vſe thereof. And what one ſubiect can more iuſtly clame your Maieſties protection, then this of the Morall Law, ſith you are not only by a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per title, <hi>Defender of the fayth:</hi> but by a common truſt committed to Kings, <hi>keeper of both Tables?</hi> The diſcharge of which truſt as it tends much to the
<pb facs="tcp:7347:3"/> honour of the great Lawgiuer, who hath made you his Vicegerent to ſee his Lawes well executed: So it is the maine propp and pillar to ſupport and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure your royall Throne. The conſideration where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, (when I ſaw theſe ſonnes of Belial thus vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermining the Kings Throne) hath prouoked my zeale both to God, and to your Maieſty, to write this ſimple Treatiſe. For to deny the Morall Law to be of any more vſe to belieuers, or to be ſo much as a rule of conuerſation, or that they owe obedience vnto it in poynt of duety and conſcience: this ſtrikes at the very root, and cutts in ſunder the k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ot, not onely of chriſtian charity, but euen of all ciuill ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, and happy vnion and communion betweene King and Subiects, Head and Members. For firſt, the rule of Gods true and vnmixed worſhip, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded in the firſt Table, is taken away: Secondly, the rule of all chriſtian and ciuill duties betweene man and man, in whatſoeuer relation they ſtand, of equality or inequality, Commanded in the ſecond Table; and all this with one ſtroke of cutting off the Morall Law from belieuers. And particularly, theſe Antinomians cut off all dutifull and conſcio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable obedience to Princes, grounded on the fift Commandement, wherein they being principall Parents, namely of our Country, all due honour and
<pb facs="tcp:7347:3"/> obedience in the Lord is commaunded to bee giuen them in the firſt place, as of children to their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Againe, on the other ſide, they breake downe the bankes, that God himſelfe hath pitched to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine the courſe of Kings, whoſe <hi>hearts</hi> in the <hi>Lords hand,</hi> like the <hi>riuers of waters,</hi> keeping within their bankes, refreſh the Land on euery ſide with their ſweete ſtreames: but being without the bankes of Gods ſacred lawes, how ſoone might they ouerflow and drowne all? Therefore it was the care of the wiſe and good God (to the end he might pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide for the hapy welfare both of the King and People) to leaue it in charge to the King of <hi>Iſraell</hi> that he ſhould haue a coppy of the Law alwaies by him, to reade therein day and night,<note place="margin">Deut 17.18, 19, 20.</note> to learne thereby to feare the Lord his God, to walke hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly among his brethren, to doe iuſtice and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to the end hee may prolong his dayes in his Kingdome, hee and his Children in the middeſt thereof. But theſe Lawleſſe Antinomians, enemyes to God, to Kings and States, would robb Chriſtian Kings of this bleſſed Booke of Gods Law, that ſoe; if they could ſtrippe them of the grace and feare of God in their hearts, letting looſſe the reynes of all honeſtie and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,
<pb facs="tcp:7347:4"/> they might vſurpe a gouernment after the luſt of man, not after the law of God, and ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitate ineuitable ruine to Princes and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weales. For take away Gods Law, and what law of man can bynde the conſcience, eyther in poynt of obeying, or of commanding? For though it hath euer beene a Maxime among the very heathen, that humaine Lawes, and ſuch as were ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified by ſolemne oathes and couenants betweene Prince and people, they held ſacred and inuiola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as that Law of the Medes and Perſians, the Kings writing and ſeale, &amp;c. <hi>Dan. 6.16:</hi> Yet the maine ground that bore vp all the reſt, was the conſcience they had, by naturall inſtinct, of Gods eternall Law written in their hearts, accuſing or excuſing; knowing that God was an auenger of the breach of lawes, oathes, couenants, ſuch as were agreeable to his Law. This then being the strongeſt ligature to combine the Head and Body politicke in a firme ſociety, whereby it becomes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincible, perpetuall, and glorious: theſe ſonnes of Belial would diſmember all. Wherein they plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhew who is their ſyre, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that lawleſſe one, whoſe Motto is, <hi>Volumus et iubemus,</hi> wee will and command; which ſtyle <hi>Platina</hi> notes to be firſt taken vp by <hi>Boniface</hi> the third, who firſt vſurped
<pb facs="tcp:7347:4"/> the Papall Headſhip ouer the Church; So as caſting off all lawes of God and man, hee became that great Beaſt deſcribed in the Reuelation, whom no law or reaſon can bound or limit; accounting it a diſparagement to his tyrannicall greatneſſe, to bee confined within the liſts of any lawes, oathes, vowes, couenants, though neuer ſo iuſt and ſacred. Now the Lord Ieſus ſo bleſſe your Maieſty, that tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pling this Antinomian Anomian hereſie, both ſyre and ſonnes, vnder your ſacred feete, you may long and happily raigne ouer your people, as a tender father ouer his children, while your chiefe care is firſt for the mayntenance of Gods pure worſhip without mixture, and for the execution of iuſtice and iudgement; theſe two being the ſumme of both the Tables, and the ſupporters of the Kings Throne, which the Lord euer defend from all Antinomian Anomian ſpirits.</p>
            <p>In this Treatiſe alſo J haue occaſionally pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the diuine inſtitution of the Lords day, our Chriſtian Sabbath, denyed by ſome. And as your raigne hath beene honoured with a pious law, for the due obſeruation of this great Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day of Christ: So, I truſt, that this my vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicating of it to its owne right of diuine inſtitution
<pb facs="tcp:7347:5"/> will not a little helpe to the better execution of that your Chriſtian law. Which that it may be more reuerently and religiouſly obſerued both in Court, City, and Country, to the purging out of profa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and to the increaſe of all chriſtian graces in your Maieſty, and vs your people; it is, and ſhall bee the daily and dutyfull prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Maieſties loyall ſubiect and old ſeruant.</hi> Henry Burton.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:7347:5"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hriſtian <hi>Reader,</hi> if this Treatiſe may ſeeme to any to bee ſuperfluous, as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending that, which noe good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians deny: yet conſidering how fruitfull theſe laſt times are in bringing forth the ſpurious ſpawnes, and monſtrous birthes of all kinds of hereſies, among which this of the Antinomians, a moſt peſtilent and pernicious ſest, is not the leaſt, which denyeth any further vſe of the <hi>Morall Law</hi> to belieuers, no not as a rule of conuerſation, as of <hi>duty</hi> to be conformed vnto: and ſeeing alſo how many counterfeit Chriſtians are ready, &amp; do daily intertaine this <hi>Libertine</hi> doctrine, which lets looſſe the raines to all licentiouſneſſe, as both the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors</hi> and <hi>Diſciples</hi> of this <hi>Antinomian</hi> hereſie, the <hi>Sons of Belial,</hi> do euidently proue in the practiſe of their lawleſſe and graceleſſe life: &amp; laſtly waighing, how this Antinomian frye is, as an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to true fayth, and the power of religion, ſo a friend to all other hereſies now on foote, ſpecially
<pb facs="tcp:7347:6"/> to <hi>Popery,</hi> ſeruing as a way maker for it, by break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing downe the wals of the City of God, that ſo <hi>Romes Troian Horſe,</hi> full of traiterous Engines and armed Engineers, may finde the eaſier reentry for the erecting of their Dagon, instead of Gods Arke: I hope thou wilt not eſteeme either my paines loſt in writing, or thyne in reading this ſmall tract. And howſoeuer there is ſmall hope, that thoſe, who haue already deepely drunke in this ſweete deadly poyſon, will eaſily admit of any Antidote or Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatiue, or ſuffer it kindly to worke vpon them, ſo intoxicated they are with the ſpirit of giddyneſse, and (I feare) many of them iuſtly giuen ouer of God to a reprobate ſenſe, hauing fallen from the truth of the <hi>Ghoſpell</hi> once acknowledged of them: Yet I doubt not, but (by Gods grace) this Treatiſe will be a meanes to preſerue all ſound and ſimple-hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted chriſtians in the true fayth of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> neuer to be ſeduced by ſuch ſpirits of errour, and perhaps to reduce into the way of the truth all ſuch honeſt-hearted poore ſoules, as haue beene beguiled by them.</p>
            <p>Onely this let mee premoniſh thee of: that whereas in the fourth page I promiſe to affix the Copy of that letter at large, which gaue occaſion of
<pb facs="tcp:7347:6"/> this Treatiſe: I haue ſince altered my minde for theſe reaſons: <hi>1.</hi> Becauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> coppy is very large: <hi>2.</hi> Becauſe I haue ſet downe the ſubſtance of it in all the particulars throughout this Tract: <hi>3.</hi> Inſtead thereof, I haue added (vpon occaſion offered, when I had ended this treatiſe) as a branch thereof, a ſhort diſcourſe toucbing the Sabbath day, the Morality whereof ſome haue of late impugned, as not binding Chriſtians in the obſeruation of <hi>the Lords day;</hi> the diuine Inſtitution whereof they alſo deny. So as if I haue not made good my promiſe in a matter of no neceſſity, nor of much moment: thou wilt pardon mee, if J haue made thee amends, in adding that, which is of farre greater importance and benefit. And if herein alſo I haue not in all poynts ſatiſfied thy iudgement to the full, concerning the Law of the Sabbath, and of the diuine inſtitution of the Lords day inſtead of the Iewes Sabbath: I ſhall (by Gods grace) ſhortly giue thee further ſatiſfaction in a fuller and ampler Treatiſe, purpoſely penned in anſwere to a booke lately come forth, which would vtterly euacuate <hi>the Lords day</hi> for the Christian Sabbath, and reduce vs to the Iewes Sabbath-day agayne. Which will bee a worke ſomuch the more neceſſary, by how
<pb facs="tcp:7347:7"/> much this Iewiſh Sabbatarian findes already many <hi>Maléferiatos homi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es,</hi> idle and giddy-brained Chriſtians to imbrace his booke, which is written with Amighty, confident, and Gyantlike ſpirit, as if the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments thereof were inuincible. Jn the meane time inioy this, and pray for mee, that God would aſſiſt me in that greater worke, and in all things that may moſt concerne his glory, and the benefit of his Church. Farewell.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine in Chriſt Ieſus</hi> Henry Burton.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Faults in the Printing, to be corrected with the pen.</head>
            <p>Page 10. liue 10: read, Calumniations. So alſo, l. 15: blot out, the p: 26: l. 17: r. cloſe. p. 27. l. 6. r to the ground. p. 30. l. 8. r. preaching. p. 33. l. 1. r. ſyllogiſticall. p. 43. l 5. r. morality of the Cmmandement. p. 51. l. 24. r: ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation. p. 52. l. 36. r. firſt-fruits. p. 55. l. 6. r. Titulus l. 9. r. ſigne. p. 56. l. 1. r, placuent. p. 57. l. 11. r. Arians, &amp; Aerians. l. 25. r. chriſtian: l. 29. blot out, his. p. 58. l. 17: r: ſlip: p. 59. l: 6. r: lye vnder. p. 60. l. 19. r. pretty reaſons. l: 30. r. impoſe. p. 61. l. 8. blot out, &amp; communing. p. 62. l. 313 r, detrect, p. 6.. l. r. commandal. 28. r. ſacred, ordinances. p. 69. in the margent. l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>. r. pawber. and l. 26. r. 515. to 15. lighter eſcapes the eye well correct.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:7347:7"/>
            <head>THE LAVV AND the Goſpell reconciled. The Euangelicall fayth, and the Morall Law how they ſtand together in the State of Grace. Vpon occaſion of a letter written by an Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomian to a faithfull Chriſtian.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat which holy <hi>Iude</hi> deemed ſo needfull to write,<note place="margin">Iude: 3:</note> and to exhort vnto; all true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians ſhould bee ready to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine; that is, earneſtly to contend for that fayth, which was once deliuered to the Saints. This was that, which the Apoſtle gaue chiefely in charge to the <hi>Philippians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. i. 27.</note> 
               <hi>Onely let your conuerſation be ſuch, as becommeth the Goſpell of Chriſt, that whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I come and ſee you, or elſe be abſent, I may heare of your affaires, that yee ſtand faſt in one ſpirit, with one minde, ſtriuing together for the fayth of the Goſpell.</hi> This is indeede that onely thing, worthy to bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for, and that with earneſtneſſe. And if thoſe two mothers before King <hi>Solomon,</hi> did ſo plead about the liuing child, which yet was mortall, and a ſinfull brood:
<pb facs="tcp:7347:8"/> how ſhould the true Church of God plead her titles to that which brings immortality, the bleſſed fruit, and iſſue of the liuing fayth. But how ſhall we know who hath beſt right to this liuing fayth? One ſaith, Mine is the liuing fayth, and thine the dead fayth; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother ſayth, No, but thine is the dead, and mine the liuing. As therefore <hi>Solomons</hi> ſword deciding the quarrell, gaue the liuing childe to the true mother: So the ſword of the ſpirit, Chriſts word, a greater then <hi>Solomon,</hi> onely can determine who is the true mother, the true Church, to which the liuing fayth of right belongeth, ſith it is deliuered to none, but to the Saints.</p>
            <p>Nor were it a matter of wonder to heare the whore of <hi>Babylon,</hi> the old Romiſh beldame, to make claime to the liuing fayth, as her naturall child, which now long agoe by ouerlaying it in the night of blacke igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and ſupine ſecurity, with her vnwealdy body (become ſo groſſe and monſtrous with the infinite ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of humaine Traditions, ſtanding in ſtead of her many ſubtractions and purloynings from the diuine truth) is ſtrangled, and become ſtone-dead; and on the other ſide, to charge the reformed Church of hauing the dead fayth, becauſe ſhe teacheth iuſtification by faith onely, with outworkes: but behold a wonder, that any ſonnes of this our deare mother Church ſhould proue ſo vnnaturall and vnreaſonable, as (and that moſt impudently, though withall cunningly, euen preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the doctrine of the Church of <hi>England</hi> to be for them, and they for it; a thing too vſuall) to impute vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her the dead fayth, as whereof ſhe is the teacher, while vnto the doctrine of iuſtification by fayth onely ſhe addeth and preſſeth the doctrine and practiſe of ſanctification, not onely as a frute, but as a duty ſprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging from the ſame. From which impious and ſenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe reproach while we ſhall purge our mother, wee
<pb facs="tcp:7347:8"/> ſhall with one buſh ſtop two gapps: both the wide mouth of Mother Babell, crying out againſt vs, that by teaching Iuſtification by faith onely, we deſtroy ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, and the impudent mouthes of the misbegot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten homebred bratts, that exclaime, we deſtroy the iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification of the true liuing fayth. And this done, we ſhall by Gods grace eyther ſo conuince theſe men, as to pull them from their dead fayth; or make it ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident to all men, as they ſhall confeſſe the dead fayth of <hi>Belial,</hi> or of <hi>Baal</hi> to be with theſe men, and the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing fayth to be onely on our ſide.</p>
            <p>Now the occaſion of our taking this taske vpon vs, is this: there is a new ſprung-vp opinion, which not onely in this City, but in ſome parts of the Country ſpreading like a Cancer, or gangrene, hath infected many, poyſoning them with a ſchiſmaticall ſpirit, and not only alienating their minds from, but opening their mouthes againſt our Congregations and Miniſters, ſo as they ſcoffe, and ſcandalize euen the ſoundeſt and ſinceareſt preaching of the word of God. They deny any vſe at all of the morall law, ſo farre as to be a rule of life and chriſtian conuerſation, after that a man is once brought to be a beleeuer in Chriſt. They allow the law no further vſe, then as to bee a Schoolemaſter to bring vs to Chriſt, and then farewell law. And if Miniſters Preach and preſſe the duties of ſanctification, theſe Antinomians ieare at them, yea and rayle on them to their very faces, calling them Anabaptiſts, and telling them, that they preach the dead fayth, and that ſuch goodly doctrines are good for nothing, but to carry men to Hell.</p>
            <p>And for my part, I ſhould not haue beleeued there had bene ſuch mouthes of blaſphemy in the world, had not mine cares bene witneſſes of them. And for a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther proofe hereof, to make it euident to others alſo (beſides other writings, which the ringleaders of this
<pb facs="tcp:7347:9"/> Antinomian or lawleſſe ſect of <hi>Belial</hi> conuey and ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter among their Diſciples) a letter, written with the chiefe ringleaders own hand (for <hi>ex vngue leonem</hi>) but conſigned or ſubſcribed with the name of one of his prime ſhe-Diſciples, and ſent to one Mr. T. may ſuffice to manifeſt their virulent ſpirits to all the world. The copie whereof is here affixed verbatim; onely I haue forborne to ſet downe the parties name at large, but onely the firſt letters of her name; concealing the Maſters name, who is the inditer and writer, altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And I follow therein the example of holy <hi>Ierom,</hi> who writing to <hi>Cteſiphon</hi> againſt the <hi>Pelagians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hieroinmus ad Cteſiphontem aduerſus Pela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gianos:</note> ſayth, No mans name is particularly touched in this ſmall worke: wee haue ſpoken againſt the Maſter of a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe opinion, who if he ſhall be angry, and ſhall write againe, hee ſhall like the mouſe bee bewrayed by his owne diſcouery, and expoſe himſelfe to receiue yet greater wounds in a ſet pitcht field. And let me alſo aduertiſe the reader concerning this letter (as alſo of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the like kinde, which I haue ſeene) that how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer it hath poyſon enough in it, yet it is ſo mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred in a goulden cup ſo couered ouer with clowdy and obſcure words, and ſo tempered with ſugared phraſes of ſcripture, as that both his Diſciples may with the leſſe ſuſpition and more delight drinke it downe, and his iuſt aduerſaries may haue leſſe cauſe to caſt it in his diſh, or to quarrell him, and bring him in <hi>Quorum</hi> for it.</p>
            <p>And that this was the ancient guiſe of Hereticks, the ſame <hi>Hierom</hi> tels vs in the ſame place where ſpeaking to the <hi>Pelagian,</hi> he ſaith: <hi>Noſti &amp;c.</hi> Thou knowſt what thou teacheſt thy Diſciples priuately, expreſſing one thing with thy mouth, and concealing another in thy conſcience: and to vs who are ſtrangers, &amp; none of thy Diſciples, thou ſpeakeſt by Parables, but to thine owne ſcholars thou vnfoldeſt thy myſteries: and this thou
<pb facs="tcp:7347:9"/> boaſteſt thou doſt, according to the ſcriptures, becauſe it is ſayd, Ieſus ſpake to the people abroad in para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and to the Diſciples within dores hee ſayth, <hi>To you it is giuen to know the myſteries of the kingdome of heauen, but to them it is not giuen.</hi> And againe, <hi>Sola haec haereſis, &amp;c.</hi> This onely is hereſie, which bluſheth to ſpeake in publike, what it feares not to teach in priuate. The rage of the ſchollars vttereth the ſilence of the Maſters. That which they haue heard in the cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, they preach on the houſe tops; that if they ſhall pleaſe their hearers, it may bee attributed to the praiſe of their Maſters: if it diſpleaſe, the fault may bee the ſcholars, not the maſters. <hi>Ideo creuit &amp;c.</hi> Thus hath your hereſie increaſed, and you haue deceiued many, becauſe you alwayes teach and alwayes deny.<note place="margin">Sententias ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtras prodidiſſe ſuperaſſ eſt &amp;c: <hi>Hieron.</hi>
               </note> It is the Churches victory, when you ſpeake plainely, what your opinion is. To ſhew your opinions, is to ſubdue them. So <hi>Hierome.</hi> Now let me appeale to the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of the Diſciples of ſuch Maſters as we ſpeake of, whither they doe not deliuer their documents and leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in plainer termes, and more perſpicuous amplifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation in their priuate ſchole or chamber by word of mouth, then they do, or dare do publikly in their looſe papers and pamphlets? Let them tell me wherein they differ or come ſhort of the <hi>Pelagians,</hi> in the guiſe of broaching and venting their opinions, noted by <hi>Ierome.</hi> And this is the nature and practiſe of all hereſie, which ſerpent-like walkes with a doubled gate, and like the ſnaile puts forth her hornes ſlowly to proue her way, but vpon the leaſt reſiſtance quickly puls them in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, or iugler-like, playing faſt and looſe with his ſpectators, or like lying Fame, which for feare is ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring at firſt, till ſpreading it ſelfe, it finde credit and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainement in the world.</p>
            <p>Yet the quicke ſighted Reader ſhall finde this let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be not altogether ſo euen ſpun, but that it hath
<pb facs="tcp:7347:10"/> many knobbs and knots of groſſe errour, which is euer vneuen, and neuer but vnlike it ſelfe, ſufficiently be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wraying a poyſonous minde, and virulent ſpirit in the author,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.5. &amp;c.</note> being of the number of thoſe, who hauing a forme of godlineſſe, deny the power thereof; from ſuch turne away. Of which ſort are they which creepe into houſes, and lead captiue ſilly women laden with ſins, led away with diuerſe luſts, euer learning and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer able to come to the knowledge of the truth. And as <hi>Iannes</hi> and <hi>Iambres</hi> withſtood <hi>Moſes;</hi> ſoe do theſe alſo reſiſt the truth, men of corrupt minds, reprobate concerning the fayth. But they ſhall proceede no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: for their folly ſhall bee manifeſt to all men, as theirs alſo was. All which, how fully it is verefied and exemplified in the Author we haue to deale with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, this little diſcourſe ſeconded with the ſubſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his owne handy worke, will abundantly teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fye.</p>
            <p>Now becauſe the letter is teadious, ſo as to anſwere to euery circumſtance would clogge our diſcourſe with many vnneceſſary and vnprofitable matters: therefore I will epitomize or contract the whole in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one briefe view, and pitch vpon ſuch points, as the Author ſtands moſt vpon, and wherein he placeth the maine ſtrength of his battalion, And firſt I will muſter vp his ſcattered skirmiſhes and brauadoes, And thoſe I finde to be diuided into two ſpeciall companies. The firſt is a brauado, ſetting forth his cauſe with many ſpecious and glorious titles; as his aſcribing it to Gods gratious calling; that it is the true liuely iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying faith which he maintaineth; (which words hee often repeateth) that it is of the houſehold of true faith; the moſt holy and heauenly calling into the true liuely iuſtifying fayth; that it is the gracious leauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Goſpell; that it is the effectuall calling to true chriſtianity, and aſſured free ſaluation; that this
<pb facs="tcp:7347:10"/> leauen is the wedding garment of Chriſts perfect ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe and that this is the good and old way which <hi>Abraham</hi> walkt in; that it is the eſtabliſhed proteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant doctrine of our Church of <hi>England,</hi> grounded vpon the word of God, which euery one ought to imbrace, if hee will be a loyall ſubiect to his Proteſtant King; againe, This is the Proteſtant fayth, this is the eſtabliſhed doctrine of our Church; that he is as one true Prophet to a great number of falſe Prophets; that he with a few more goe with a right foot to the truth of the Goſpell; ſuch as call the people to a chearefull, zealous, godly life, onely for and by the ioy and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of free iuſtification (but marke how) deepely conſidered; onely thoſe few doe apply the law purely and truely; that theſe are the few foreſayd true mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Chriſt, and (ſuch as follow them) the true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuers; that they onely bring in the true meanes of true ſanctification, and of doing all good workes; that theſe are the true teachers, who doe truely eſtabliſh the law; that theſe are the onely true miniſters, and their followers the onely true people of God; that this doctrine is and may bee proued in euery point with two or three plaine ſcriptures, and two or three plaine teſtimonies of Orthodox Proteſtant writers. Theſe and the like bee the glorious guildings, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with hee doth ſo fairely inammile his leaden cauſe, which anon will come to the Teſt.</p>
            <p>The ſecond company, wherewith he skirmiſheth all along, is of ſuch reproches, as hee caſts vpon all thoſe that are aduerſaries to his opinion. I take them in order as they lie. That to auouch the contrary is a ſinfull preiudice of Gods truth; that it is a blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the true liuely iuſtifying fayth; ſuch are too much leauened with the ſowre leauen of the deuouter ſort of Phariſees, which with the falſe brethren a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Galatians</hi> leauened and corrupted the faith
<pb facs="tcp:7347:11"/> of the <hi>Galatians;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Thus the pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificians, where they find cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainety of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, they call it preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp;c.</note> and that with a conceited holineſſe of doing and keeping the morall law; this is a dan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gerous leauen of the Phariſees, which vnder the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour, and conceit and opinion of ſincerity and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to God, and zeale of God, is but hipocriſie; Chriſts marriage garment is now a dayes eagerly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, and ſubtilly betrayed with a <hi>Iudaſſes</hi> kiſſe; in this regard theſe are the perilous times, wherein men and women are euer learning, and neuer able to come to the truth of the aſſurance of their free ſaluation, and that there is in a manner now no fayth on the earth, becauſe the dead fayth, before God, is no fayth; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be varniſhed and guilded ouer with a blinde prepoſtrous zeale, and opinion of obedience, and walking in all gods commandements, as <hi>Paul</hi> before his conuerſion was in this blind zealous dead fayth (which phraſe is very frequent with him) that it is another Ghoſpell; that the blinde zealous dead faith thinkes it knowes ſomething, when it knowes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing as it ought to know, that they are not ſome few teachers among vs that trouble the people of God by Preaching another Goſpell: but (eſpecially when God meanes to puniſh an vngratefull Church and Nation) many falſe teachers;<note place="margin">This great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, Iwis.</note> as of old, there are many hundred falſe Prophets to one true Prophet; hanging, relying, and depending, yea bragging of their obedience, workes, and weldoings, and keeping of the law; theſe bad miniſters and teachers that trouble the people of God are, and for the iuſter iudgement and ſcourge of the great vnthankefull multitude euer haue beene the greateſt multitude; and theſe are deuided into two ſorts: the firſt ſort are ſuch, as are euill beaſts, ſlow bellies, that vſe to preach a little for their liuing ſake, and for their bellie, but care not for the ſauing of ſoules, but for their eaſe, their pompe, and worldly eſteeme; and thoſe miniſters make onely Hoggschriſtians; that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:7347:11"/> trampling free iuſtification and the Pearles of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell vnder the feete of their durty affections, doe care for nothing, but rooting in the earth, and filling the belly: but the other ſort of bad teachers, although their right eye alſo of true fayth bee out, and doe more deepely delude themſelues and others in the dead fayth, yet they haue the light of nature more ſtrongly ſtirring in them, deſcribed <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.14.15. where it is ſayd, that the Gentiles which haue not the law doe by nature the things conteined in the law, which ſhew the effect or worke of the law written in their hearts, their conſciences alſo bearing witneſſe, and their thoughts accuſing them, that is, with feare of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, when they doe ill, and will preach it, as the true Goſpell I warrant you: and excuſing them, that is, hoping to ſpeede well, when they doe well; and this light of nature they varniſh ouer with titles of the Goſpell, whereby eſpecially young Miniſters being carryed with a prepoſterous zeale of Gods glory, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.2.3. in workes and conceited weldoings, they ſlight ouer fayth, and free iuſtification with a wet finger, thinking with the Papiſts by a carnall vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of them, that they are quickly, or rather lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned too faſt, and ſo doe preach neyther true law, nor true Goſpell, but a corrupting, blending and marring of both law and Goſpell; whereby they put out the right eye of the greateſt multitude of zealous profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, they drowne them with themſelues in the dead fayth, and inſtead of a true fayth in Chriſts righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, doe make them to rely and hang vpon their owne holineſſe, workes, and well-doings, whereby people are euer troubled in conſcience; or elſe glory with the Phariſes <hi>Luke.</hi> 8.11. in a prepoſtrous, falſe, baſtard ſanctification, and Anabaptiſticall mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and obedience, in doing the law of God, flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from no true loue or charity; and ſo, as the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:7347:12"/> profaine Miniſters doe make dogg-chriſtians; ſo greedily feeding vpon the fifthy pleaſing carrion of the ſecret lurking vaine glory of their owne holyneſſe, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, workes, and well-doings; that theſe moſt <hi>Iudas</hi>-like and traiterouſly trample the pearle of free iuſtification, and free grace vnder the feete of their Phariſaicall affections, and doe not onely fall a barking like doggs at the few<note n="*" place="margin">Meaning thoſe of his Antino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mian and lawleſſe ſect.</note> foreſayd true Miniſters of Chriſt, and ſo trouble the true beleeuers with all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of caluminations, raylings, and ſlanderings, as that they are againſt ſanctification, and good workes, whereas they onely bring in the true meanes of true ſanctification, and of doing all good workes; and that thoſe true teachers deſtroy the law, when they truely ſtabliſh the law; &amp; with ſuch-like innumerable calumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations; but alſo ſticke euen violently like doggs to fly in the true Miniſters and people of Gods faces, and are ready (if they can) to teare out their very throats, with bitter hatred, and cruell perſecution; are not theſe truely Chriſts dogg-chriſtians? the Diſciples of ſuch falſe maſters plainely declaring, that whilſt they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for the law, they are both in words and deedes the greateſt deſtroyers of the law, and that their brag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging obedience is moſt grieuous diſobedience, all their holy ſanctification is dubble ſin and iniquity, and that their whole worſhip of high eſteeme with men is idolatrous and abomination before God, traiterous to their King, and dangerous to the betraying and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of their whole Country and Kingdome, wherein ſuch liue. Therefore in my hearty loue, and in the ſincerity of my bettered affections, I pray you take heed of this blinde, zealous, dead fayth, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent not your ſelues in the carnall knowledge of free iuſtification, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thus farre of his skirmiſh. Wherein thou mayeſt (good reader) obſerue how he magnifieth himſelfe as
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:7347:12"/> the onely true Prophet oppoſed by many hundred of falſe Prophets; thoſe hee rankes together with their hearers, and ſeuerall congregations, into two compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies: the one a heard of hoggs, the other a kennell of doggs: and of theſe two he makes vp the vniuerſall body of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as which God hath giuen vp to bee plagued with ſuch miniſters of the blind dead fayth, as his vſuall manner of language is to call it. So as in ſumme he makes the Church and nation of <hi>England</hi> to be an accurſed Iſle of hoggs, and doggs. Againe, for all this, note how ſliely, like the ſubtile ſerpent, hee ſeekes by inſinuation to patronize his doctrine vnder the authority of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> eſtabliſhed doctrine, as grounded thereon, and conſonant thereunto, and ſo conſequently vnder the Kings protection: (a peſtilent peece of policy and practice) though by neceſſary conſequence, hee makes the Defender of the fayth no better, (that which my very thought abhorreth) then one of his hogg, or dogg-chriſtians: and on the other ſide labours to make all his aduerſaries odious, as being in their do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctrines enemyes to the King and State; (a notable practiſe of heretickes in all ages) and ſuch are all Miniſters in Court, City, Country, all Courtiers, Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, Country-men, that follow not this man in his conceited true liuely fayth.</p>
            <p>Come we in the next place to his maine battalion, which hee rangeth into 3 ſquadrons. Namely hee ſets downe the ſtate of the doctrine in 3 Propoſitions, which he cals his 3 Proteſtant poſitions. The firſt is: that the horrible filthineſſe of ſin is ſuch to Gods infinite, pure, and righteous nature, that God cannot but abhorre, curſe, and deteſt the creature, that hath any ſin in his ſight: as theſe, and ſuch like ſcriptures teach: <hi>Deut.</hi> 27.26. 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.4. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12.15. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 59 2. <hi>Iob.</hi> 15.16.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:7347:13"/>
            <p>The ſecond is: I beleeue, that for remedy of this my miſery by ſin, God by the power of his imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on doth, though myſtically, yet ſoe truely cloth mee with the wedding garment of his ſons perfect holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and righteouſneſſe, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 61.10. that all my ſins, both of my perſon and works being truely aboliſhed, not out of me, 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.8. that there may be place for fayth, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.1. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.18.19. to 21. but yet vtterly aboliſhed out of Gods ſight <hi>Col.</hi> 1.22. I and all my workes are of vniuſt made iuſt before God, that is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly holy &amp; righteous from all ſpot of ſin in the ſight of God freely by faith only without works. And I ſay, By fayth onely without workes, becauſe onely true fayth ſeeth this, and onely true fayth inioyeth this. And thus by Chriſts ſtripes am I healed, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 53.5. <hi>And ſo God is well pleaſed and at peace with mee. For being iuſtified by fayth, we haue peace with God, Rom.</hi> 5.1. <hi>And am truely bleſſed, Rom.</hi> 4.6. <hi>For as many as are of this fayth of free iuſtification, are bleſſed with faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Abraham, Gal.</hi> 3.8.9. <hi>and ſhall be certainely glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified: for whom God iuſtifieth them he alſo glorifieth, Rem.</hi> 8.30. All which Proteſtant poſition of free iuſtification is abundantly and clearely taught by theſe and ſuch like ſcriptures: <hi>Eſa.</hi> 43.25. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 44.22.23. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.29. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.26. 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Reu.</hi> 1.5.6. <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.24. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.21.22. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.17.18.19.21. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.26.27. <hi>Reu.</hi> 3.18. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.22.23. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.4. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.30. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.14. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 62. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.8.9. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.15. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.4.</p>
            <p>The 3 is: my third poſition is, that this true fayth of free iuſtification doth infallibly inflame the heart with true loue, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.6. which makes the true belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to breake off from; and mortifie his former cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt and profane conuerſation, and brings forth a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claratiue obedience, and redineſſe to euery good worke, and a free and cherefull walking in all Gods
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:7347:13"/> will and commandements declaratiuely to manward, which is true ſanctification: as theſe, and ſuch like ſcriptures teach, <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.11. to 15. 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.5.6.9. <hi>Eph:</hi> 2.10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.22.23.24. <hi>Math.</hi> 5.16. This is the Proteſtant fayth; this is the eſtabliſhed doctrine of our Church: theſe are the 3 poſitions, that (here hee makes the woman-Diſciple to ſpeake) I haue too lately receiued, and which haue ſo changed mee out of the blinde zealous dead fayth, into the true liuely iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying fayth.</p>
            <p>Thus you haue his 3 Proteſtant poſitions (as hee calls them) ſet downe word for word. which an indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent reader, yea a ſound Proteſtant peruſing, and knowing no more of the authors minde, then what is here expreſſed: hee would at the firſt ſight perhapps take all for harmeleſſe and ſound doctrine. But when he ſhall conſider how all theſe poſitions (as Proteſtant as they bee) ſtand in oppoſition to all that doctrine, which is generally taught by the moſt ſound, learned, and orthodox Diuines in <hi>England,</hi> and ſo (I may ſafely ſay) in all the world: then hee may well ſuſpect a Pad in the ſtraw, and a ſerpent to lurke vnder the greene leaues, and ſome thing more in it, then at the firſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth.</p>
            <p>For touching the firſt poſition: What one Proteſtant Diuine doth not hold and teach, that ſin is moſt deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to God, which his pure eyes cannot behold, and that it makes a man odious in Gods ſight? Witnes the bitter and curſed death of the ſon of God himſelfe, which hee ſuffered for ſin; otherwiſe wee had all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained vnder the curſe, left to eternall perdition, the iuſt puniſhment and reward of ſin, if it had not bin re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued by Chriſt. So as herein the author hath no co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of accuſation againſt his hoggs and doggs, his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries: but this firſt Poſition ſerueth onely as an vſher to lead in the reſt, or as a harbinger to take vp the beſt rome in mens conceit for the reſt of the traine
<pb facs="tcp:7347:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> by prepoſſeſſing the readers minde with an expectation of ſutable doctrine in that which followeth.<note place="margin">Num, 23.8.</note> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we ſhall finde, that he playes but the cheater, who ſhowing one peece of good gold out of his purſe would perſwade his gull, that his purſe is full of ſuch, when all the reſt is but counters, or counterfet gold double guilt.</p>
            <p>For the ſecond poſition: what Proteſtant Miniſter of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> of what ranke ſoeuer, bee he reckoned among his hoggs, or among his doggs, that holdeth not, and teacheth not, that the onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy to remooue mans miſery by ſin is Ieſus Chriſt, his death and paſſion, his obedience actiue and paſſiue, his whole righteouſneſſe freely imputed of God to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery true beleeuer? What Proteſtant, Diuine, or other, but holds iuſtification to be by fayth, freely without workes? And that thoſe whom God iuſtifyeth, hee ſo acquiteth them in aboliſhing their ſin, that hee remembreth it no more, but caſts it behinde his backe, ſeeth it not any more, in asmuch as he doth graciouſly for his ſonnes ſake not impute it to them. So as what needes all that heaping vp of places of ſcripture? as if none but the Author tooke notice of them: or as if his doctrine were ſo vnknowne or doubted of, as it needed ſuch a cloud of proofes.</p>
            <p>Yet ſome particulars in this poſition would bee a little talked with all. As 1. where hee ſayth, That all ſins in the beleeuers are vtterly aboliſhed out of Gods ſight, by being not imputed. This is moſt true. Yet it puts mee in minde of that which I heard long agoe ſcattered abroad by this very Author, that God ſeeth no ſin in his children. Which Aphoriſme taken vp of the vulgar, may breede in them, that beleeue not, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous thoughts, and reſolutions voyd of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of ſin. Therefore this poynt would be a little opened. True it is, God ſeeth no ſin in his beleeuing
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:7347:14"/> children, for which hee inflicteth the curſe, or any ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactory penalty vpon them. Thus when <hi>Balack</hi> would haue had <hi>Balaam</hi> to curſe Gods people, hee anſwered, <hi>How ſhall</hi> I <hi>curſe, where God hath not cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed?</hi> And v. 19. <hi>God is not as man, that hee ſhould lye, or repent; hath he ſayd, and ſhall hee not doe it? Behold</hi> I <hi>haue receiued commandement to bleſſe; and hee hath bleſſed, and I cannot reuerſe it.</hi> And hee renders the reaſon: <hi>He hath not beheld iniquity in</hi> Iacob, <hi>neyther hath he ſeene preuerſeneſſe in</hi> Iſraell; <hi>the Lord his God is with him, and the ſhout of a King is among them. Surely there is no inchantment againſt</hi> Iacob, <hi>nor diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation againſt</hi> Iſraell. <hi>For Christ hath borne</hi> Iſraels <hi>ſin, in him hath God, the Iudge, fully puniſhed it, his iuſtice is fully ſatiſfed for all</hi> Iſraels <hi>debts.</hi> So that all being ſatiſfied and diſcharged in our ſurety, Chriſts righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe and ſatiſfaction made ours, now God ſeeth not ſin in his beleeuing children, as a iudge to puniſh them: yet he may be ſayd to ſee as a father, to chaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe them. Or when he chaſtiſeth his childe, hee ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to ſee his ſin, though done away in Chriſt, and pardoned in Gods Court, to the end his childe may come to ſee it, and ſo haue the euidence of pardon ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vnto him in the Court of his owne conſcience, And this is that, which all ſound Proteſtant Miniſters teach and beleeue.</p>
            <p>A ſecond thing I note in his ſecond poſition, is, if not an abſurdity, yet an obſcure ſpeech: his words are, All my ſins both of my perſon and workes are truely aboliſhed, not out of me: that there may be place for fayth. Why? Are ſins aboliſhed actually by imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, before fayth bee wrought, that the aboliſhing of ſin makes way to fayth? True it is, <hi>Chriſt hath taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way our ſins, and by death aboliſhed death, before we haue fayth to apply it; for our fayth is from the merite and vertue of his death.</hi> Otherwiſe, I know not what ſenſe
<pb facs="tcp:7347:15"/> to make of his words; vnleſſe hee meane that fayth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone takes place in the beleeuer, working and doing all infallibly and freely, (as elſe where he expreſſeth himſelfe) without the Law of the ten Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments:</p>
            <p n="3">3 I note a falſhood in it: for he ſayth, <hi>All my workes are of vniust made iuſt before God.</hi> What theſe works are, I finde in other of his ſcatered pamphlets: to wit all naturall, ciuil, religious, ſanctified actions, which being in themſelues (as he ſayth) foule and filthy, are made perfectly holy and righteous by free iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Now this is a thing both impoſible, and were alſo vniuſt, for God to doe it. It is impoſſible for God to make a worke, that is vniuſt to bee iuſt. Indeed Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt arrogateth this omnipotent, or rather impotent power, as deriued from God, to make <hi>ex iniuſtitia iuſtitiam,</hi> righteouſneſſe of vnrighteouſneſſe: but Gods omnipotency ſtretcheth not to make an vniuſt worke to be iuſt. For then he might ſeeme to be both impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident, and vniuſt, in appointing his ſonne to take away ſin by the ſacrifice of himſelfe, in caſe God could haue made of ſin no ſin by his meere omnipotency. Indeede God can make a thing to ceaſe to bee, or hee can make a thing to bee, which had not a being, as hee did all the world: but hee cannot ſo aboliſh a thing, as to cauſe the former being of it not to haue bene a being after it hath once actually bene. So of a wicked worke; God is ſo powerfull, ſo good, ſo iuſt, as that hee cannot make the wickedneſſe to bee good: for that implies a contradiction; but hee can and doth ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſh the wickedneſſe of our workes by Chriſt, by not imputing of them; as if it had neuer bin. But to ſay, our workes are of vniuſt made iuſt, this as it is a phraſe not vſed in ſcripture, ſo in the Antinomians ſenſe it tends to the bringing in of a heauenly ſtate of perfection in this life. For he would inferre herevpon
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:7347:15"/> that a man once in Chriſt, iuſtified, is altogether with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſin in Gods ſight; abuſing that place of <hi>Iohn,</hi> 1, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.6, 9. Where he concludes, that the iuſtified man not onely cannot ſin, but alſo <hi>abſtaineth from all appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of euill.</hi> Theſe are his very words. And hence is that curſed hereſie of the <hi>Pelagians,</hi> and <hi>Pontifici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> reuiued by the Antinomians, that there is ſuch a prefection in this life, as a man may liue altogether without all ſin: for all his ſins of vniuſt are made iuſt, ſaith he. The nomination whereof is a ſufficient con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation. <hi>For in many things we ſin all, Iam.</hi> 3.2. <hi>And if we ſay wee haue no ſin, wee deceiue our ſelues and the trueth is not in vs.</hi> 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.8.</p>
            <p n="4">4<hi rend="sup">d</hi> I note another falſehood, where he ſayth, By fayth onely with out workes, freely, I am perfectly holy and righteous from all ſpot of ſin in the ſight of God: (and why? (becauſe only true faith ſeeth this, and only true fayth inioyes this. How? are we iuſtified by faith freely, becauſe only true fayth ſeeth this? What if true fayth, while during the time of ſome temptation the exerciſe of it is ſuſpended, do not ſee, nor inioy the fruite of iuſtification? muſt we therefore paſſe ſentence vpon our ſelues, that we are not iuſtified? nay certainly we are therefore iuſtified from all ſin, becauſe God not imputing ſin ſeeth no ſin in vs: and not becauſe we ſee and inioy our reconciliation and peace with God. For though God be continually pacified towards his faithfull children in Chriſt, yet doe not they allwayes by the act of fayth ſee and inioy Gods fauour towards them. This was <hi>Dauids</hi> caſe; and is, and may be the caſe of euery child of God. Yet whenſoeuer wee doe ſee and enioy our iuſtification, by hauing peace with God through Chriſt, we doe by the eye and apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of fayth ſee and enioy it. But our ſeeing and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioying is not the cauſe that wee are iuſtified, but the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:7347:16"/> conſequent effect and fruit of it, being apprehended by fayth.</p>
            <p n="3">3<hi rend="sup">ly</hi> For his 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Poſition, therein ſtand his Triarian forces; here his files are ſo doubled, and the rankes are ſo cloſſe, that it ſeemes to be impregnable, impene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trable. But howſoeuer they ſtand thicke without, yet they are thin and hollow within, ſo that being but once by a wedge diuided, they are able no longer to abide the field. Therefore obſeruing it well, I finde ſundry aduantages to bee taken. Firſt, from his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending of fayth in the efficacy of it, that it infallibly inflames the heart with true loue, making the true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuer to breake off his former corrupt conuerſation, &amp;c. Secondly, that hee vſeth one word twice, to wit, Declaratiue, obedience Declaratiue, and a free and cherefull walking in all Gods will, and Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments declaratiuely to manward. Which may ſeeme to ſome to be eyther idle, or a riddle; but we ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the myſtery of it by and by. In the meane time, all this hitherto in his 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> poſition hath no other ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, but of ſound and orthodox doctrine; agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Scriptures, and ſo to the doctrine of our Church, if there bee no more in it, then what the outer rinde makes ſhow of. For what Proteſtant Church, or what one ſound Proteſtant of our Church doth not teach, or beleeue, that that moſt noble and diuine La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy grace of true ſauing and liuing fayth, doth infallibly (to vſe his owne word) inflame the heart with loue, which makes the true beleeuer to breake off from, and mortifie his former corrupt, and profane conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, and brings forth a declaratiue obedience, and redineſſe to euery good worke, and a free and cheerfull walking in all Gods will and Commandements decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to manward, which is true ſanctification. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we all agree. Whereis the difference then? Yea but the author comes afterwards in the ſame poſition,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:7347:16"/> and (although he proteſt theſe his poſitions to be the Proteſtant fayth, and the eſtabliſhed doctrine of our Church) he proclaimes a defyance againſt the blind zealous, dead fayth, as meerely oppoſite to this his true liuely iuſtifying fayth, And this dead fayth, whoſe is it? by whom is it taught? by whom intertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned? Euen by the vniuerſall bulke and body of our Church, which he deuides into two ſides, the left ſide conſiſting of profane ſenſuall hoggs, and the right ſide of zealous Anabaptiſticall Doggs, as he ſtiles them. Now if the caſe ſtand ſo, that all thoſe proteſtants ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally, whom he calls doggs, and hoggs doe hold the ſelfe-ſame doctrine in truth, as the author ſetts downe in words, and yet theirs is the blind zealous dead faith, and his the truely liuely iuſtifying faith: it concernes vs a little more narrowly to examine his words, to ſee whither ſome myſticall ſenſe bee not couched in them; or whither hee hath dealt not ſo candidly, nor ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geniouſly (as by his roauing and rauing language may iuſtly bee ſuſpected) but hath kept vp ſome reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uations as precious pearles; which if hee ſhould vent among ſo many hoggs and doggs, as he liues amongſt, hee might iuſtly feare, leſt the one ſort ſhould, and that worthily, trample them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their feete, and the other turne vpon him, and all to teare him. But now it being brought to the vpſhot, whither hee, or we haue, the true liuing iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying fayth: hee muſt permit vs perforce (we bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our warrant from God) to mak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a priuy ſearch, and to rifle his Cabbinet, to ſee whither hee haue this Pearle of the Kingdome, yea, or no. Nor are wee ingaged to doe this in regard onely of our faith towards God, as wee are Chriſtans, but alſo of our fidelity and loyalty to our King the Lords Annoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as wee are ſubiects, for asmuch as hee challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth all men, that hee that will bee a loyall ſubiect to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:7347:17"/> his Proteſtant King, ought to embrace this doctrine of fayth, which he onely, the <hi>A per ſe</hi> Doctor, doth teach.</p>
            <p>Wherein then is the maine difference betweene vs, that makes his the onely true liuely iuſtifying fayth, and ours the blinde, zealous, dead fayth? Surely in this; that his fayth is ſo liuely, actiue, vigorous, and potent, perfect, and compleat, that of it ſelfe it produceth all the fruites of ſanctification, without hauing any thing to doe with the word of God, eſpecially the morall law, as a rule of our actions, or as a glaſſe of our im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections: when as wee on the other ſide acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that our fayth at the beſt eſtate during this life, is not ſo perfect, and euery way compleat, but as a lampe it needeth the continuall ſupply of the holy oyle of Gods ſpirit of grace, to cauſe it to flame forth the more in the workes of ſanctification, which grace of the ſpirit is miniſtred and ſupplyed vnto vs by the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry of the word of God, as the Oyle-pipe through which it runneth: and for as much as in the ſtate of grace and fayth, <hi>we know but in part, and propheſie in part,</hi> and conſequently our fayth is imperfect, being mingled with much ignorance; therfore we haue need of the Morall law, wherof both the old and new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are a large commentary, both as a rule whereby to frame our thoughts, words, and workes, and alſo as a glaſſe, wherein looking the face of our ſoules, and beholding our ſpeckes and imperfections, we may get them waſhed in the fountaine of Chriſt blood, and may make ſtraight pathes vnto our feete,<note place="margin">Heb. 12, i3:</note> leaſt that which is lame be turned out of the way, but rather that it bee healed. This is that perfect law of liberty, wherein who ſo looketh, and continueth therein, hee being not a forgetfull hearer, but a doer of the worke this man ſhall be bleſſed in his deed: <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.25. This
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:7347:17"/> is that glaſſe,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 3.18.</note> wherein wee beholding the glory of the Lord, are changed into the ſame Image from glory to glory, euen as by the ſpirit of the Lord. So farre are we from holding a ſtate of perfection of faith in this life, as though our faith could doe all things of it ſelfe, and did not neede a dayly ſupply of grace, which muſt bee procured by the word of God, eyther preached, or read, or meditated and conferred vpon, and that alſo by the meanes of prayer, <hi>Lord increaſe our fayth.</hi> But this our Aduerſary ſhutts out the law quite, as out of date to a true beleeuer, and of no vſe at all, not ſo much as to be a rule of life and conuerſation; his liuely faith doth all, and hath noe neede of the word of God to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect or aſſiſt it.</p>
            <p>Now that this is the ſumme of his doctrine concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his liuely faith, yee may gather from his owne words, ſaying, fayth infallibly inflames the heart with true loue, making the true beleeuer to breake off his former corrupt conuerſation &amp;c. This word Infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, implies, that faith doth by a continued and vnin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted act inflame the heart with loue to doe all workes of ſanctification, and ſo it hath no neede of Gods word as a rule to bee guided by, but the ſpirit, is inſtead of the word. But you will ſay, So much is not expreſſed in the letter. True. But you muſt know that this is the doctrine, which he priuately inſtilleth into his Diſciples. As in one of his ſcattered writings I find theſe words, that this fayth of free iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion doth cauſe vs to walke infallibly in the ſteps of the workes of our father <hi>Abraham,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by like <hi>Abraham,</hi> freely without the law of the ten Commandements, wee walke holily, righteouſly, and ſoberly in all Gods Commandements declaratiuely to manward. Yea comming ſometimes to conteſt with mee, and to charge mee for preaching the dead fayth, himſelfe did vtter ſo much to mee by word of mouth,
<pb facs="tcp:7347:18"/> that after a man is once inlightned by fayth, the ſpirit guides him, ſo as he hath no need of the word, or of the Morall law for a rule to direct him. This Doctrine is ſo familiar among his Diſciples, as they profeſſe it, and are prowd of it, ſo farre are they from making ſcruple or dainety of it, as once to deny it. So that this is one of the markes and properties of his liuely fayth, that it hath no neede of the Morall Law to bee a rule vnto it in poynt of conuerſation, or in the workes of ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication; otherwiſe neyther is it the true liuely fayth, nor this the true ſanctification.</p>
            <p>A ſecond property and prerogatiue of this his liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fayth is this, that it oweth no obedience to the Morall Law in poynt of duty. Hee denyeth the works of ſanctification to bee duties. What are they then? Fruits, ſayth he. So ſay we too; fruits they bee, yet duties too. Here is the difference then. Becauſe wee ſay the fruits of fayth are duties, therefore hee ſayth ours is the dead fayth. Al this hee hath auouched, and that moſt vehemently (as his manner is) to my face. And howſoeuer he hath not in plaine words expreſſed ſo much in this his letter, as being more ſhy and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telous what hee publiſheth abrode, hauing bene ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered by me and others, and puzzled with ſome argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which hee could not anſwere, but ſayd hee would anſwere them when they were written: Yet ye may eaſily gather ſo much out of his writing. For he cals the obedience of a beleeuer onely declaratiue, and to bee done declaratiuely to manward. Note it well. This declaratiuely to manward excludes all du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to Godward. For elſe what vſe is there in this place eyther of <hi>Declaratiue,</hi> or much leſſe, <hi>To manward?</hi> For all obedience in conuerſation is declaratiue: and all declaratiue is to manward. So as all this mans obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience is to manward, in poynt of declaration, but none to Godward in poynt of duty. For if it bee of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:7347:18"/> duty in obedience to Gods law, then his fayth alſo ſhould be the dead fayth. But herein ſtands the prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiue of his true liuely fayth, that as it doth not ſo much as reflect the eye vpon the morall Law, as to learne obedience from the rule thereof: ſo much leſſe doth it acknowledge it oweth any obedience there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto as a duty to God.</p>
            <p>On the contrary we for holding and teaching, that the Morall Law, and ſo Gods word ſtands not onely for a rule of direction for ſanctified obedience, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo requireth of the faythfull a cheerfull yet dutyfull conformity thereunto: we (I ſay) for this very cauſe muſt heare, Hoggs, or Doggs, Hogg-chriſtians, or Dogg-chriſtians, as holding the blind, zealous, dead fayth. So thus ſtands the ſtate of the queſtion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene vs about the liuing and the dead fayth, and herein we come now to ioyne yſſue.</p>
            <p>Firſt then wee are all agreed on both ſides, that the true liuely fayth is no other, but that whith the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures teach and allow for the true liuely fayth, which promiſed, and granted, I argue thus.</p>
            <p>That fayth,<note place="margin">Propoſition.</note> which the Scriptures teach and allow for the true liuely iuſtifying fayth, that, and no other, is the true, liuely, iuſtifying fayth.</p>
            <p>But the Scriptures teach and allow that, and no other,<note place="margin">Aſſumption,</note> for the true, liuely, iuſtifying fayth, which reſting on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on Chriſt for iuſtification by the onely imputation of his righteouſneſſe, doth notwithſtanding looke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Morall Law of God as a rule of Chriſtian conuerſation, and ſanctification, acknowledging the conformity thereunto as a duty which God requireth of euery true beleeuer: according to that, <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.74.75. <hi>That we being deliuered from the hands of our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, ſhould ſerue him, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore this fayth and none other is that, which
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:7347:19"/> the Scriptures teach and allow for the true liuely iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifying fayth.</p>
            <p>The Propoſition is vndeniable. The Aſſumption I proue. And firſt from the very giuing of the Morall law in mount <hi>Sinai.</hi> For it was giuen in, and by, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Chriſt the Redeemer.<note n="*" place="margin">Deut. 18.18.</note> As the Apoſtle ſayth, <hi>It was giuen in the hand of a Mediator:</hi> which <hi>Mediator</hi> was perſonally <hi>Moſes:</hi> but typically <hi>Chriſt,</hi> of whom <hi>Moſes</hi> was a type and figure. And Chriſt was that heauenly<note n="*" place="margin">Exo. 25.40. Heb. 8.5,</note> Patterne or Antitype, according to which were all thoſe things deliuered to <hi>Moſes</hi> in the Mount; yea not onely the Ceremoniall Law, but alſo the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Law giuen by Chriſt himſelfe, where hee ſayth, I <hi>am the Lord thy God, which hath brought thee out of the Land of Egypt, out of the houſe of bondage?</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon followes, <hi>Thou ſhalt haue none other Gods before me. Thou ſhalt not make &amp;c.</hi> For theſe words (I <hi>am the Lord thy God, whicb brought thee out of the Land of Egypt, out of the houſe of bondage,</hi>) are a preface to the whole Decalogue or ten Commandements, ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting forth the Author of them vnto us, not onely by his name <hi>Iehouah,</hi> but by that neere relation of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federacy, or Couenant of grace made to vs in Chriſt, ſaying, <hi>Thy God.</hi> And that this is the very Couenant of grace made to vs in Chriſt, vnder which the Law is giuen, appeareth by this, that the words of the Preface containe not onely a hiſtory of that peoples tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall deliuerance from the Egyptian bondage: but alſo, and eſpecialy the myſtery of the Redemption of all the true Iſrael of God by Chriſt, or their ſpirituall deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance from the bondage of ſin and Satan. This is a thing moſt cleare, though few obſerue it. For was not the Paſchall Lambe ſlaine, and the blood ſprinck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vpon all Iſraels doore poſts, and the Angell paſſed ouer them, and <hi>Egypts</hi> firſt-borne were ſlaine, and Gods firſt-borne deliuered? And was not Chriſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figured
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:7347:19"/> thereby, as the <hi>Lambe ſlaine from before the foundation of the world?</hi> Yea all thoſe paſſages of Gods people from <hi>Egypt</hi> to <hi>Canaan</hi> came to them in <hi>Types,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſayth.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10:</note> Beſides other types, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue here two notable ones, which ioyntly are preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to our purpoſe: firſt of Chriſts aſcenſion: ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, of ſending the Holy Ghoſt. 1. the hiſtory in <hi>Exo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi> well obſerued makes it plaine, that vpon the 40<hi rend="sup">th</hi> day after their comming out of <hi>Egypt, Moſes, Aron,</hi> and <hi>Hur,</hi> went vp into the Mount, where <hi>Moſes</hi> hands are by <hi>Aron</hi> and <hi>Hur</hi> ſupported, while <hi>Ioſhuah</hi> with Gods people fight againſt <hi>Amaleck.</hi> Now <hi>Moſes</hi> the Prophet, <hi>Aron</hi> the Prieſt and<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hur</hi> ſignifieth a Prince, and he was of the family and tribe of <hi>Iuda.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Hur</hi> the Prince (for ſo was his name by interpretation) all put together, were a type of Chriſt, who on the fortith day after his reſurrection, aſcended into the Mount of Heauen, where, as our Prophet, Prieſt, and Prince, hee holds vp the hands of his interceſſion for his Church mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, while ſhe fights with ſpirituall <hi>Amaleck,</hi> Sin, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, Antichriſt, the World, the Fleſh, &amp;c. The other Type I note, was iuſt 10. dayes after, which from <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt</hi> makes 50. dayes, and that was the giuing of the Law in Mount <hi>Sina,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts. 2,</note> and therefore called the Iewes Pentecoſt, and we know, that on the day of Pentecoſt iuſt 50 daies after Chriſts Reſurrection, and 10 daies after his Aſcention, did the Father and Chriſt ſend downe the Holy Ghoſt in his manifold gifts and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to lead his people into all truth, and to reueale fully the Law of Chriſt vnto them. Now therefore the as the type, &amp; thing typed are (for their vſe to the faythfull people of God) one and the ſame thing: <hi>So as the ancient Iſralites did all eate the ſame ſpirituall meate, and did all drinke the ſame ſpirituall drinke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.3.4.</note> 
               <hi>for they drank of that ſpirituall rock that followed them; and that Rock was Chriſt:</hi> So that giuing of the Law in Mount <hi>Sina,</hi> being a type of the comming down of the holy Ghoſt bringing &amp; reuealing the Law of Chriſt to his Church both of them in ſumme and vſe are to the faithfull one
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:7347:20"/> and the ſame law; for though they differ in the manner of adminiſtration, and in the meaſure of manifeſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yet not in the matter it ſelfe, Chriſt being the ſumme and matter of both. And thus we clearely ſee, that the Morall Law giuen in Mount <hi>Sina,</hi> being giuen by <hi>Iehouah</hi> our God in Chriſt the Redeemer, and that vnder the couenant of grace, being giuen to the Iſrael of God in the old Teſtament, to which the comming downe of the Holy Ghoſt in the new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament fully anſwereth; that it remaines as a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall rule of a holy life to all Gods people to the end of the world. So that here, by the way an inuincible argument is hence drawne, to proue the perpetuall morality of the ſabbath to the end of the world, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all Antiſabbatarians, becauſe it was giuen vnder the couenant of grace to be kept. But wee will reſerue the further diſcuſſing of this poynt to the choiſe of all, leaſt the intermingling of it here ſhould interrupt the maine matters in hand.</p>
            <p>Obiection. But the Apoſtle ſayth, <hi>The law is not of fayth,</hi> How then comes the Law to bee giuen vnder fayth?</p>
            <p>Anſwere. The Law, in that place, is to bee taken for the firſt Couenant, to wit, of workes, giuen to <hi>Adam</hi> in Paradiſe in the ſtate of innocency; which hath no communion with fayth belonging to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond couenant, namely, of grace. But the Law, as it was giuen in Mount <hi>Sina,</hi> the literall veile being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooued, was not deliuered as the firſt Couenant, but as a rule of conuerſation to the faythfull vnder the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Couenant.</p>
            <p>Obiection. But the Apoſtle calls the giuing of the Law in Mount <hi>Sina</hi> the firſt Couenant in oppoſition to the ſecond. as <hi>Agar</hi> to <hi>Sara,</hi> the bond-woman to the free, <hi>Sina</hi> to <hi>Sion</hi> and <hi>Hieruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſwere. The Apoſtle compares it ſo onely in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:7347:20"/> of the literall killing ſenſe, to which the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall <hi>Iew</hi> was captiuated, and thereby ſlaine, while not looking vnto Chriſt the Redeemer, that brought his people out of the ſpirituall <hi>Egypt</hi> and bondage, they ſought to bee iuſtified by the workes of the Law, which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> beats downe the to ground in that Epiſtle to the <hi>Galatians.</hi> But to the belieuing <hi>Iewes</hi> the Morall Law was none other, but the <hi>ſweete yoake</hi> and <hi>light burthen</hi> of Chriſt, while they behold him as it were on the top of <hi>Iacobs</hi> ladder a Redeemer of his people by his owne innocent blood, whereby hee expiated all their breaches of the Law, fulfilling the Law for them. And in no other regard doth the Law in Mount <hi>Sina,</hi> and that in Mount <hi>Sion</hi> ſtand oppoſite, but as the letter to the ſpirit, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6. while the carnall Iewes could not diſerne the pith of the ſpirit vnder the barke of the letter: or by way of compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, the one excelling the other in the manner and meaſure of mynifeſtation, as 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.10. Wherevpon the learned and iudicious <hi>Caluin</hi> vpon thoſe words, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.24 fayth, <hi>that the Iewes liberty was hidden vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the vaile of ceremonies, and of the whole economy, or diſpenſation of the Law, by which they were then gouerned:</hi> So that in externall ſhew nothing but ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitude appeared. Yet the ſeruile generation of the Law hindred not, but that the godly fathers, who liued vnder the old Teſtament, had for their mother the ſpirituall <hi>Ieruſalem, which is free.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o that it was partly the Iewes blindneſſe, and partly the veile couering thoſe Moſaicall myſteries, which made that Law in <hi>Sina</hi> ſeeme to bee no other, but the Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of workes made with <hi>Adam</hi> in his Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency.</p>
            <p>Queſtion. But here by the way it may bee asked, wherein doth the firſt Couenant, and the ſecond chiefly differ?</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:7347:21"/>
            <p>Anſwer. There are ſundry oppoſite differences be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the two Couenants.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The firſt Couenant was of mans works: the ſecond of Gods grace, and theſe two in the poynt of iuſtification are oppoſite one to the other. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.6.</p>
            <p n="2">2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi> The firſt couenant was made with <hi>Adam,</hi> and all his poſterity vniuerſally: the ſecond onely with <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeede, called the womans ſeede. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. to wit, Chriſt, and all the Elect. ſo <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.1.</p>
            <p n="3">3<hi rend="sup">ly</hi> The firſt couenant ſtood vpon mans owne righteouſneſſe, the ſecond ſtands vpon anothers righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, to wit, Chriſts rigteouſneſſe, made ours by imputation.</p>
            <p n="4">4<hi rend="sup">ly</hi> The firſt couenant ſtood vpon the mutability of mans will, ſo as it was quickly broken: but the ſecond ſtands firme vpon the ſure foundation of Gods immutable will, good pleaſure, and eternall purpoſe in himſelfe, ſo as it can neuer bee broken, being an euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Couenant.</p>
            <p n="5">5<hi rend="sup">ly</hi> The firſt was a couenant of iuſtice without mercy: the ſecond a couenant of iuſtice and mercy to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, iuſtice fulfilled by Chriſt, and mercy extended in and for Chriſt to all the Elect.</p>
            <p n="6">6 The firſt Couenant had no other reward reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to the firſt <hi>Adam (from the Earth earthy)</hi> but what was confined to the earthly Paradiſe: but the ſecond hath the Kingdome of Heauen ſet open in Chriſt <hi>(the ſecond Adam, the Lord from Heauen)</hi> vnto all the Elect.</p>
            <p>Theſe and the like differences betweene the firſt Couenant and the ſecond well conſidered, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred together, will plainely ſhew, that the Law gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnder Chriſt the Redeemer in Mount <hi>Sina,</hi> was not that firſt Couenant of workes. For beſides the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:7347:21"/> fore alledged reaſons, there is mention made of Gods mercie in the ſecond Commandement; and of the promiſe of the land of the liuing, the Kingdome of Heauen tiped in <hi>Canaan,</hi> in the fifth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Which mercy and kingdome were not compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended in that firſt Couenant of workes. But ſo much of the firſt proofe of our Aſſumption, which was, that true iuſtifying fayth though it reſts vpon Chriſts righteouſneſſe onely for iuſtification, yet it lookes vpon the Morall law as a rule of Chriſtian conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and acknowledgeth the obedience thereunto as a duty, which God requireth of euery true belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer.</p>
            <p>The ſecond proofe is in <hi>Math.</hi> 5.<note place="margin">Reade for this from the 16. verſe to the end of the chapter.</note> Where our Maſter Chriſt in his diuine ſermon vpon the Mount, expound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to his diſciples, and all faythfull hearers, and doth as it were giue them a Commentary vpon the Morall law, which the ſame Chriſt deliuered to <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> in the Mount; which hee ſets before his ſcholars as a rule of the duties of ſanctification, and chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an conuerſation,<note place="margin">Math. 5.20.</note> in which <hi>their righteouſneſſe they muſt exceede the righteouſneſſe of the Scribes and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees, otherwiſe they could not enter into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heauen.</hi> But how ſhall Chriſt eſcape the cenſure, as one that preacheth the dead fayth? ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I know not, while his faythfull Miniſters preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame doctrine, are cenſured as preaching the blinde, zealous, dead fayth, and are called doggs for their labour.</p>
            <p>But becauſe Chriſt preached and preſſed the Morall Law as a rule of Chriſtian obedience, and called that alſo their righteouſneſſe: therefore did he teach, or meane, that this was their righteouſneſſe in the ſight of God? Nothing leſſe. For he that ſaid,<note place="margin">Math. 5.20.</note> 
               <hi>Except your righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:7347:22"/> exceede the righteouſneſſe of the ſcribes and Phariſes, yee ſhall not enter into the Kingdome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen:</hi> ſayd alſo, <hi>VVhen yee haue done all theſe things that are commanded you, ſay wee are vnprofitable ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, we haue done that which was our duety to doe.</hi> Marke, he cals our obedience to the Law of God our duty: yet ſo, as wee are not thereby iuſtified. And yet wee preach the ſame doctrine of our Maſter Chriſt, muſt bee rated as Doggs, as preaching the dead fayth.</p>
            <p>The 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> proofe is from that exquiſite forme of Prayer preſcribed by Chriſt, in the fifth petition, <hi>Math.</hi> 6, 12. <hi>Forgiue vs our debts, as wee forgiue our debters.</hi> All ſins are debts to God. All ſins are breaches of the Morall Law: therefore the keeping of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Law is a debt that wee owe to God. The Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is Chriſts. The Aſſumption is the <hi>Apoſtles.</hi> So as nothing remaines for the Aduerſary to deny, but the Concluſion.</p>
            <p>The fourth proofe is from the Apoſtles words, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.6. (that which the aduerſary alſo alledgeth for the proofe of his third poſition) <hi>In Ieſus Chriſt, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther circumciſion auaileth anything, nor vncircumciſion, but fayth which worketh by loue.</hi> Loue to God, and to our neighbour is a duty we owe to God, and to our neighbour. But the Morall Law is the rule of this loue. Therefore fayth working by loue lookes vpon the Morall law as a rule of thoſe duties of loue we owe to God and our neighbour. That loue is a debt, the Apoſtle prooueth, <hi>Ro.</hi> 13.8. <hi>Owe no man any thing, but to loue one another;</hi> ſo that is a debt, that we owe one to another. And if loue be a debt to man, then much more to God. Againe, that the Morall Law is a rule of this loue, the ſame Apoſtle prooueth in the ſame chapter, v. 9. For this, <hi>Thou ſhalt not commit adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry:
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:7347:22"/> Thou ſhalt not kill: Thou ſhalt not ſteale: Thou ſhalt not beare falſe witneſſe: Thou ſhalt not couet: and if there be any other Commandement: it is briefely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended in this ſaying, namely, Thou ſhalt loue thy neighbour as thy ſelfe. Loue worketh no ill to his neighbour: therefore loue is the fulfilling of the Law</hi> So that the concluſion remaines firme, that fayth working by loue lookes vpon the Morall Law as a rule of thoſe duties of loue we owe to God, and our neighbour.</p>
            <p>The fifth proofe is from the Apoſtles words <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.1. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I <hi>beſeech you therfore brethren, by the mercies of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Propoſition,</note> 
               <hi>that yee preſent your bodies a liuing ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, holy acceptable to God, which is your reaſonable ſeruice: And bee not conformed to this world,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aſſumption,</note> 
               <hi>but bee tranſformed by the renewing of your minde, that yee may proue what is that good, and acceptable,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Concluſion,</note> 
               <hi>and perfect will of God, &amp;c.</hi> Now from this generall exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hee deſcendeth to particular duties, as ſo many branches ſpringing from our reaſonable ſeruice of God. From thence to the very end of the Epiſtle. Whence I argue thus.</p>
            <p>All Chriſtian duties of loue to God, and to man are branches of our reaſonable ſeruice of God.</p>
            <p>But the Morall Law containes all chriſtian du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of our loue to God, and to our neighbours.</p>
            <p>Therefore the keeping of the Morall Law is our rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable ſeruice of God.</p>
            <p>The Propoſition is euident by the whole context of the Apoſtle in the foreſayd part of his Epiſtle The Aſſumption is vndenyable, proued before.</p>
            <p>The ſixt proofe is from 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4, 1. <hi>&amp;c. Further more then we beſeech you brethren, and exhort you by the Lord Ieſus, that as yee haue receiued of vs, how yee ought to walke, and to pleaſe God: ſo yee would abound more and more. For yee know what commandements wee
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:7347:23"/> gaue you by the Lord Ieſus. For this is the will of God euen your ſanctification, that yee ſhould abſtaine from fornication.</hi> The exhortation is very forcible, and full of waight. Hee preſſeth it by the authority of the <hi>Lord Ieſus:</hi> he mindeth them of it, as one of thoſe leſſons he had deliuered formerly by word of mouth, and they had <hi>receiued:</hi> hee calls it a duty, <hi>How yee ought to walke:</hi> yea a duty to God, <hi>How yee ought to walke, and pleaſe God:</hi> hee calls it a ſpeciall <hi>commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> which hee gaue them by the <hi>Lord Ieſus</hi> as which the Lord Ieſus gaue him in charge to deliuer to them: hee calls it <hi>the will of God:</hi> he calls it their <hi>ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now what is all this which the Apoſtle here aymeth at? What, but this: <hi>That yee abſtaine from fornication?</hi> Whence I argue thus:</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Propoſition,</note>Abſtinence from fornication is a part of keeping of the Morall Law.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Aſſumption:</note>But this abſtinence from <hi>fornication</hi> is a duty accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to God, is a doctrine to be taught by the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Chriſt, to be receaued by the people of God, is a <hi>commandement of the Lord Ieſus,</hi> it is <hi>the will of God,</hi> it is our <hi>ſanctification,</hi> or a fruite and effect of it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Concluſion.</note>Therefore the keeping of the Morall Law is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded of God, of Chriſt, as a duty to all true belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers.</p>
            <p>To what part of this Argument will the aduerſary anſwere? To the Propoſition? That hee dare not: for the Law ſayth. <hi>Thou ſhalt not commit adultery.</hi> To the Aſſumption? That he cannot; for that is the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, in the fore alledged place. Therefore I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with this concluſion, That the keeping of the Morall law is commanded of God and of Chriſt, as a duty to all true beleeuers. When I vrged this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:7347:23"/> or the<note n="*" place="margin">as rhis. What ſoeuer is Gods will we ſhould doe, is our duty to doe: But the doing of Gods Law is Gods will wee Should doe, therefore it is our duety to doe Gods law, ſo farre as we are able. Now all this is plainely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded by the Apoſtle. <hi>This is the will of God euen your ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, that ye ſhould abſtaine from fornication.</hi> To abſtaine fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fornication is a part of kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the Moral Law, and what is true of a part, is true of the whole, as <hi>Iam.</hi> 2.10, 11.</note> like in forme ſyelogiſticall, out of this very place of the Apoſtle, to this our aduerſarie occaſionally face to face, and had, to ſatiſfie his demande repeated it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer twice or thrice: hee could not giue a preſent anſwere, but deſired to haue it written downe. But I expect not an anſwere, becauſe none can be giuen to this which is here written.</p>
            <p>No, can he not in all his budget finde an anſwere? doth hee not (as I heare hee was wont to doe at leaſt) carry his trunk-hoſe full farſed &amp; ſtuffed with Proteſtant Authors, as <hi>Luther, Zanchee, Paraeus,</hi> with ſundry others of good note, that with their graue authority and reuerend names he may the more eaſily impoſe vpon his credulous and ignorant Diſciples, who admire that moſt, which they vnderſtand leaſt: cannot he out of all theſe beate out an anſwere to theſe things; For of theſe he braggs much in the concluſion of his letter. But till hee can bring ſome, I will content my ſelfe to bring his belweather Author, euen <hi>Luther,</hi> whoſe no leſſe puiſſant, then elegant, and heauenly ſpeech (wherewith I will for this time conclude this ſhort diſcourſe) ſhall run full butt vppon, and puſh downe all that he hath ſayd for his pretended, counterfet, falſe, hereticall, ſcandalous, Anabaptiſticall, libertine fayth: <hi>Luthers</hi> words are: <hi>Admittimus quidem Moſen legendum, &amp; audiendum a nobis, vt predictorem &amp; teſtem Chriſti. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inde vt petamus ab eo exempla optimarum logum &amp; morum Cetaerùm dominium in conſcientiam nullo modo concedimus ei; ibi mortuus et ſepultus eſto; nemoque ſciat vbi ſepulchrum eius ſit:</hi> we indeede admit of <hi>Moſes</hi> to bee read &amp; heard of vs as a Prophet &amp; witneſſe of Chriſt: Againe, that wee may fetch from him examples of good lawes and manners. But dominion ouer the conſcience (to a man in the ſtate of grace, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.10.) wee by no meanes yealde him; there, let him bee dead and buried; and let no man know where his ſepulchre is. So <hi>Luther.</hi> And
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:7347:24"/> in his argument vpon the <hi>Galatians: Sum quidem pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, &amp;c.</hi> I am indeed a ſinner according to this preſent life, and the righteouſneſſe of it, as the ſon of <hi>Adam</hi> where the Law accuſeth me, death raigneth and will deuoure mee: but aboue this life I haue another righteouſneſſe, another life, which is the Sonne of God, who knoweth not ſin and death, but is righteouſneſſe and life eternall: for which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo this dead body of mine ſhall be rayſed vp againe, and freed from the bondage of the Law and of ſin, and toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the ſpirit it ſhall bee ſanctified. So both theſe remaine while we liue here, the fleſh is accuſed, exerciſed, made ſad and contrite with the actiue righteouſneſſe of the Law: but the ſpirit raigneth, reioyceth, and is ſaued by paſſiue righteouſneſſe; becauſe it knoweth it hath the Lord ſitting in heauen at the fathers right hand, who hath aboliſhed the Law, Sin, Death, and hath t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ampled vnder feete all euill things, hath led them captiue, and tryum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phed ouer them all. So he.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now God forbid, that I ſhould glory, but in the croſſe of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, by whom the world is crucified vnto me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 6.14.</note> 
               <hi>and</hi> I <hi>vnto the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For in Chriſt neyther Circumciſion auayleth any thing, nor vncircumciſion, but a new creature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">15</note>
               <hi>And as many as walke according to this rule, peace bee on them, and mercy, and vpon the Iſrael of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I thought here ſhould haue bin an end. But as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe is,<note place="margin">16</note> One abſurdity begets a thouſand; as one of <hi>Lerna</hi> his 7 heads being cut off, 3 grew in the place there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.<note place="margin">Parua m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tu pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo, mox ſeſe at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollit in auras, Ingred túrque ſolo, et caput inter nubila condit. Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum horren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum ingens, &amp;c. Virgil. Aenead.</note> Such is the nature of hereſie, which of a ſmall ſeede growes to be an hiddeous monſter, if it bee not ſtrangled in the firſt conception. Like Fame, which for feare at firſt is ſmall: but finding entertainment with Dame Credulity and loquacity, growes bold and big vpon it. Or like a ſmall leprous ſpot in the beginnig, which quickly runneth ouer the whole body. Or like a drop of ſweet poyſon, which at firſt goes pleaſantly downe, but in a ſhort time inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:7347:24"/> it ſelfe to the infecting of the vitall ſpirits, and ceaſſeth not, till it hath wrought its mortall effect. Or like a Gangreene, or like a <hi>Canker,</hi> as the Apoſtle compares it. This Antinomian leproſie doth ſpread, and get ſtrength, and boldneſſe euery day, euen vnto impudency &amp; madnes.</p>
            <p>And the reaſon it finds ſo many diſciples to imbrace it, becauſe cutting off ſanctification, denying it to be a du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, (as one of their Diſciples ſaide, <hi>Away with this ſcuruy ſanctification.</hi>) and putting all vpon an imaginary fayth, and perfection in Chriſt: it becommeth ſo much the more plauſible to fleſh and blood, which is ſo prone and ready to liſten after any doctrine, that giues liberty to their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamed luſts. So that when ſuch Diſciples heare their tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers ſay, <hi>Beleeue onely, and ſo be merry in Chriſt, ſing care away to the duety of ſanctification, away with mortificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Repent no more, for yee are perfectly iuſtified, God ſeeth no ſin in you, yee are perfectly ſaued,</hi> and the like: no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell if being carnall, and they hypocriticall perſons, they catch at ſuch doctrines, as may nuzzle them in their car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall luſts, as is too apparent by the fruite which groweth neceſſarily from ſuch <hi>a roote of bitterneſſe, whereby many are defiled.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For perſwade a man once, that being in Chriſt, and ſo iuſtified from all his ſins,<note place="margin">Montaniſtae om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem panitentiae virtutem è me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dio ſuſtulerunt. Hieronead Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellinam. Et lib. <hi>2.</hi> adu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rſus Iouinianum. ſe Centuria: <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> hee hath no more neede of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance: and what a flood-gate is opened to all impiety, when there is noe more conſcience of ſin? Thus they reuiue the hereſie of the Montaniſtes, who denied repentance to be needefull. This they ground vpon <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.11. <hi>Not laying againe the foundation of repentance from dead works.</hi> Whence they conclude, that beleeuers haue no more to doe with repentances, where as the Apoſtle there ſpeakes of the Doctrine, not of the practiſe of repentance, repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing thoſe Hebrewes, that they were no better proficients i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Chriſts ſchoole, when inſtead of being <hi>able to teach o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> they were ſtill A B C darians, hauing need to be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichized
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:7347:25"/> in the very common rudiments &amp; knowne Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Religion, as <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.12. Againe they ſay, that they are as pure from all ſin in Chriſt, and as perfect in righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe and holineſſe, as Chriſt himſelfe is: alledging that in <hi>Iohn.</hi> 1 <hi>Iohn.</hi> 4.17. <hi>Herein is our loue made perfect, that we haue boldneſſe in the day of iudgement: becauſe as hee is, ſo are we in this world.</hi> Hence they conclude ſuch abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute perfection to bee in the beleeuer, as in Chriſt now glorified in heauen. And therefore when they ſay, that a beleeuer is perfectly ſaued in this life, they expreſſe themſelues in plaine words to meane, that a beleeuer is perfectly glorified in this life, and that there is noe diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betweene our ſtate here and in heauen, but onely in our ſenſe and apprehenſion. I ſhould not (I confeſſe) haue beleeued, that euer any man, endued with common ſenſe and reaſon, would haue ſo much as once conceiued, much leſſe uttered ſuch a ſenſeleſſe and monſtrous Paradox, had I not my ſelfe heard one of their Antinomian Miniſters affirme ſo much to me and others together. For I asking him what difference there was betweene the ſtate of grace here, and that of glory here after: hee anſwered, none at all, but in our ſenſe and apprehenſion. And thereupon another Miniſter asking him, whither we were perfectly glorified in this life: he anſwered, wee were; whereupon I, abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſuch an inſolent and Luciferian ſpeech, preſently a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyded his company and further ſpeech. To this height of pride are they come, who teach the empty and windy faith of Iuſtification againſt Sanctification, the fruit of a true liuely fayth. But are wee perfectly glorified in this life, ſo as it differs not from that in heauen, but in our ſenſe and apprehenſion? Then when a iuſtified man ſinneth, it is but in his ſenſe and apprehenſion, if that; or rather, they are in this poynt without ſenſe &amp; apprehenſion of ſin. Then when wee are afflicted, diſeaſed, and the like, it is not ſo indeede, but onely <hi>in our ſenſe and apprehenſion;</hi> becauſe a man perfectly glorified can neyther ſin, nor ſuffer any ſorrow, diſeaſes, or death. Yea our fayth is no more <hi>the
<pb facs="tcp:7347:25"/> foundation of things hoped for, and the euidence of things not ſeene, we haue no longer hope of eternall life, but in our ſenſe and apprehenſion; For wee are already poſſeſſed of the thing hoped for, we are already perfectly glorified.</hi> O ſenſeleſſe ſtupidity! But they vrge, <hi>As he is, ſo are wee in this world;</hi> he is pure, perfect, vndefiled, therefore are we ſo to. Therefore, ſay they, wee are ſo perfect, as wee cannot be more. But St <hi>Paul</hi> ſheweth plainely the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of St <hi>Iohn,</hi> ſaying:<note place="margin">2 Cor. 3, 8.</note> 
               <hi>But we all with open face beholding as in a glaſſe the glory of the Lord, are changed into the ſame image from glory to glory, euen as by the ſpirit of the Lord.</hi> Now though from hence they would inferre, that we haue the ſame image of Chriſts glory in full perfection: yet the next words <hi>(Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> glory to glory)</hi> plainely ſhew, that though the ſtate of grace bee a glorious eſtate, as being an initia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of glory, being begun here in the ſoule: yet wee goe from one degree of glory and grace vnto another, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer attaine to full perfection, till <hi>this mortall ſhall put on immortality, and this corruption ſhall put on incorruption.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor, 15. Rom. 8.29.</note> So that the image of Chriſt which wee beare vpon vs here, is a conformity vnto Chriſt our Head in the participation of his glorious graces, but in ſuch a proportion, as here we are capable of, and as God hath diſtributed <hi>to euery man the meaſure of fayth.</hi> And the ſtate of grace is in a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall growth here, as 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.12.13. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.7 <hi>The path of the righteous</hi> being a perpetuall progreſſe, like <hi>to the morning light, ſhining more and more vnto the perfect day: Prou:</hi> 4..18. But why doe I ſpend arguments a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch as deny vndeniable Principles?</p>
            <p>But thus wee ſee, how a falſe and imaginary faith, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of theſe men doe dreame, begets in them ſuch damnable imaginations, &amp; high preſumptions, euen to the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of grace, while they would ſtretch it beyond the line. No maruaile therefore if they aboliſh quite any further vſe of the morall law, ſyth they deny Sanctification it ſelfe, as a duty preſcribed and commanded in the law. <hi>Exo.</hi> 19.5.6. So that if the Doctrines of theſe men might
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:7347:26"/> preuaile, what could bee expected, but a deluge of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſme and profaneſſe, and all lawleſſe licentiouſnes and diſſoluteneſſe to ouerflow and drowne the world? For they cry downe and aboliſh all duties contained and commanded in the Morall Law, both towards God, and towards men. Doe we thinke theſe men can be good ſubiects to their Prince, who deny they owe him any ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in the way of duety enioyned by the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,<note place="margin">1 Pet, 2, 17,</note> 
               <hi>Honour thy Father and Mother;</hi> whereof one maine branch is, <hi>Honour the King?</hi> And if they doe not of due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty honour their King on earth, how ſhall they honour their King in heauen? To inſtance in the fourth comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement: they quite abrogate the Morall Law to beleeuers, and conſequently the fourth commandement, which is the ſanctification of the <hi>ſabbath-day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But they reply, that the Iewiſh Sabbath-day is abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, and therefore Chriſtians haue nothing to doe with the commandement, no more then the reſt of the Deca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue. I anſwere: It followeth not: for though the Iewes ſabboth day be aboliſhed, yet there remaines a ſabboth to bee kept of Chriſtians, ſeeing that the commandement of the ſabboth is Morall, and ſo no leſſe perpetuall, then all the reſt. For if none of the reſt of the commandements be aboliſhed: then neither the fourth And ſo though the cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall part of the Iewes ſabboth be abrogated, yet not the morality of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> But how, or wherein was the Iewes Sabbath day ceremoniall?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> In two regards; firſt, becauſe it was appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them to bee a memoriall of their deliuerance out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> as <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.15. where the Lord ſayth. <hi>And remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that thou waſt a ſeruant in the Land of Egypt, and that the Lord thy God brought thee out thence through a mighty hand, and by a ſtretched out arme: therefore the Lord thy God commanded thee to keepe the Sabbath day.</hi> So that the Iewes were commaunded to keepe the ſabbath day in a thankefull remembrance of their deliuerance
<pb facs="tcp:7347:26"/> from the Egyptian bondage; <hi>therefore the Lord thy God commanded thee to keepe the Sabbath day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> But in <hi>Exo.</hi> 20.11. the Sabbath day hath relation to the Creation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> True, yet herein <hi>Deuteronomy Moſes</hi> tells them, that euen then, when this commandement was giuen the Lord had a ſpeciall reſpect to the deliuerance from <hi>Egypt;</hi> and therefore hee ſayth, <hi>the Lord commanded thee,</hi> as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring to the time paſt, when the Law was giuen. And in that reſpect the Sabboth day was to them ceremoniall. Secondly in regard of ſome ceremonies proper (as ſome ſay) to that Nation, being inhabitants of the Land of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan,</hi> a hot climate; as the not kindling of a fire on the Sabboth, as alſo the not dreſſing of their meat in that day, which was in remembrance of the Manna in the deſert: whereof they gathered enough for the ſabboth on the day before, God miraculouſly and plentifully prouiding it for them. But in very truth, &amp; (ſo farre as I can yet conceiue, till I be conuinced otherwiſe by better reaſons, then I haue yet ſeene) that obſeruance of not kindling a fire, nor dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of meate on the ſabboth (which was lawfull &amp; allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vpon all other feſtiuall dayes) was not ſo much proper to that people in regard of their hot Country and climate, as in regard of that Moſaicall Pedagogie and diſpenſation, vnder which that onely people and Church was ſubiuga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and ſubiected, ſo as this not kindling a fire, &amp; not dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of meate, was a meere Ceremony Moſaicall, a type of the eternall ſabbath, brought in by Chriſt in his reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which puts an end to all ſabbaticall ceremonies, as theſe are, which typed the eſtate of the euerlaſting ſabbath, wherein is no need of bodily prouiſion. For in heauen, there ſhall bee neyther kindling of fire, nor dreſſing of meat, nor the like. Whereupon <hi>Iſychius</hi> in leuit. lib. 6. cap. 19. ſpeaking of the <hi>Omer</hi> of <hi>Manna,</hi> which euery one was to gather euery day, and two before the ſabboth, <hi>An Omer</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>was ſo much, as could feede one man. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he would teach and instruct them of the intelligible reſt,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:7347:27"/> and end of the world, becauſe then it was impoſſible to boyle, or worke, or gather.</hi> Some againe limit the not dreſſing of meate ro the time of their trauell in the Deſart 40 yeares, during the Manna, and not to extend to the Land of <hi>Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> where the Manna ceaſſed. And this lis not improbable, ſith their iourney in the wilderneſſe was to type out the time of out heauenly Country, where all the prouiſion for the body ſhould ceaſſe. Some alſo reſtrayne the not kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of a fire to the worke of the Tabernacle onely (as Vatablus in <hi>Exod.</hi> 35.3.) but I ſee no probabillity hereof, ſeeing the Prieſts about the Tabernacle had liberty on the ſabbath to performe their rites, as ſacrificing, and the like. Yet (by the way) the abrogation of theſe cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies ought not Chriſtians to turne into ſurquedry and exceſſe of feaſting, (as too many doe) ſo abuſing their chriſtian liberty: but to bee vſed with all ſobriety, ſuch as may not hinder, but helpe the holy ſpirituall dueties of this day by a due refreſhing of the body, for neceſſity, not for ſuperfluity.</p>
            <p>Now theſe Ceremonies dying together with the whole Moſaicall economy, which ſtood in types and Ceremonies, yet the Morality remaines a perpetuall ſuruiuer in, and with, and vnder the Goſpell. For elſe, if the Morality of the Sabbath were antiquated and aboliſhed, then alſo the whole Decalogue. But the Decalogue, or ten Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments remaine ſtill in force, not onely in their curſe and full rigour to all tranſgreſſing Infidels, ſuch as are out of Chriſt, but alſo as a rule of holy conuerſation to all true beleeuers. And that the Morall Law ſtill remaines as a rule of Chriſtian obedience to euery true Iſraelite, appeareth by the very manner of giuing of it in Mount Sinai. For it was giuen by the Lawgiuer Chriſt the Redeemer of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who ſayth, I <hi>am the Lord thy God, which haue brought thee out of the Land of Egypt, out of the houſe of bondage:</hi> and thereupon inferreth, <hi>Thou ſhalt haue no other Gods be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me,</hi> &amp;c. Now the deliuerance out of the Egyptian bondage what was it, but a type of our ſpiritual deliuerance
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:7347:27"/> from ſin and ſathan by Chriſt? And therefore by his owne argument it followeth, that the ſame Morall Law giuen by and vnder Chriſt to the Iewes in the old Teſtament, is propagated and perpetuated to all chriſtians in the new Teſtament, and ſo conſequently the Sabbath, as touching the morality of it.</p>
            <p>Thus the Morall Law is no leſſe a rule to beleeuing chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians then it was once to the beleeuing Iewes, all one ioynt ſpirituall ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> to whoſe poſterity this Law was giuen. And thus alſo by the ſelfe ſame reaſon, the fourth Commandement for the ſanctification of the ſabbath is ſtill in force with the Chriſtian Church, as well as the other 9. vnleſſe (as the Papiſts haue by their ſacrilegious practiſe nimmed away the ſecond Commandement out of their vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar Catechiſme, and by their corrupt gloſſes guelded the maſculine ſenſe of it in their Doway Bibles) wee will take their part in the polluting and profaining the Sabbath, by denying the perpetuall morality of it, and ſo leaue but two Commandements for God (according to the Popiſh acompt) in the firſt Table; or rather none at all, when by this meanes there is noe day allowed for his ſeruice, no nor mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to teach vs the true worſhip of the onely true God, &amp; the honour due vnto his name, which meanes is the publique Miniſtry of his word, together with publique and priuate inuocaſion.</p>
            <p>So that the whole worſhip and ſeruice of God, and his ſauing knowledge for mans ſaluation (to ſpeake nothing of bodily refreſhing, and workes of Charity, for the reliefe of the poore) hauing a neceſſary dependance, as touching the externall meanes, vpon the due obſeruation of the fourth Commandement in the Morality o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it: who can deny the kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of the Sabbath to be Morall, but he muſt withall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cliame open enmity to Gods worſhip, and mans ſaluation;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> But the Sabbath day of the Iewes being wholy ceaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, as being buried in Chriſts graue, wherein hee reſted all that day, and ſo fully kept it: of what force is it with chriſtians any longer? or what morality remaines of it
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:7347:28"/> to bee obſerued by vs?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> As the Iewes Sabbath day was a preciſe ſeauenth day, which no doubt was by ſucceſſiue reuolution obſerued by Adams generations from the ſeauenth day of the Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſanctified by Gods owne reſt, (for we reade of it, in <hi>Exo.</hi> 16. which was before the giuing of the Law in <hi>Sinai,</hi>) but with all had an addition of a new relation to the typicall Redemption from <hi>Egypt,</hi> as we noted before, in which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard it was ceremoniall: So (as ceremoniall) it was ſubiect to be abrogated, and changed from a Legall, into an Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicall Sabbath, which the Scripture calleth the Lords day. Although ſome are bold to deny, that the Sabbath was at all obſerued by the Old Church, vntill <hi>Moſes</hi> time, and ſo till the Law was giuen in <hi>Sinai.</hi> But this ſeemes to bee a groundleſſe opinion, if not alſo Godleſſe. For though the Scripture makes no mention of the keeping of the Sabbath, vntil <hi>Exod.</hi> 16.5. &amp;c. yet both that mention goes before the ſolemne bidding of it in Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> and doth alſo ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently inferre, that the Sabbath was in vſe before that time, as being fiiſt inſtituted in Paradiſe. For elfs, as a learned Diuine of our Church hath noted vpon this very occaſion: <hi>It is abſurd for any man to prepare a thing</hi> 2000 <hi>yeares, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the vſe thereof.</hi> And <hi>Exod,</hi> 20.11. the very reaſon and ground of mans obſeruation of the Sabbath is there giuen to bee Gods owne inſtitution of it, which was his actuall ſanctifying and bleſſing of it by his owne reſting on that day from the workes of Creation. Though otherwiſe the fourth Commandement, being a part of the Law written in <hi>Adams</hi> heart, needed not any expreſſe Commandement, more then the reſt did; ſauing that this hath a Memento ſet vpon it, as being moſt ſubiect to neglect and prophanati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and that the Lord himſelfe was pleaſed to aſſigne his owne ſeuenth day for reſt and ſanctification to thoſe former ages. But to proceed: Here it may be demanded, what is that morality of the fourth Commandement, which yet is in force with chriſtians? For anſwere: None will queſtion (but the Antinomian, who altogether denyeth the whole Morall
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:7347:28"/> Law to be in force, ſo much as a rule to beleeuers vnder the Goſpell, the morality of the Sabbath to bee yet of force and vſe with Chriſtians. Onely ſome differ both about the manner of it, how it is impoſed, and how exacted of chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and about the matter of it. For firſt, they denie that the fourth Commandement hath any thing to doe with the Lords day, which is the chriſtian Sabbath. Againe they deny that the fourth Commandement reacheth further, then to maſters of families, exempting ſeruants from imputation of ſinne, in caſe they worke at their maſters command. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they deny the Lords day is by any diuine inſtitution, humane onely, and therefore not of the ſame force with the fourth Commandement. Fourthly, (for the matter) they deny that the vacation and abſtinence from ſeruile labour, or the ordinary workes of a mans worldly calling, is any part of the morality of the fourth Commandement, but a meere ceremony, and ſo abrogated. Yea they goe further, and ſay, that howſoeuer the generality of that Commandement to keepe a Sabbath, wherein God might bee honoured, was Morall: Yet the ſpeciality of it, namely to keepe, Firſt, one day of ſeauen: Secondly, the ſeauenth: Thirdly, one whole day: Fourthly, with preciſe vacancy from all worke, was meerely ceremoniall, and ſo the ſpecialities of the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement are vaniſhed, though for the generality of it, it is a law of nature and remaineth. So they. Here then be ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry things, which offer themſelues to bee ſcanned. And to make way, Firſt where they call the bodily reſt, obſerued once by the Iewes, a poynt of exact and extreame vacation from euery kind of worke, &amp; which chriſtians haue nothing to doe with all: This is but a buggbeare, or ſcarcrow to fright Childiſh chriſtians from ſo much as looking backe to the fourth Commandement, in the keeping of the Lords day. For firſt an extreame vacation was not exacted of the Church of the Iewes; as in caſe of extreamity, or vrgent ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, they might worke, yea for the ſauing of a poore Aſſes life, by pulling him out of the pit on the Sabbath day; as our Sauiour conuinceth the carping Iewes.</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:7347:29"/>
            <p>How much more in extremities of more importance, as the quenching of a ſcath fire, or defending of their City, or Country, by repelling the inuading, or beleaguring enemy? yea in ſuch caſes not to beſtirre themſelues, and to vſe their vtmoſt labour and skill, not onely turned into ſuperſtition, but many times proued their bane and ruine. Among ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry inſtances in this kinde,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioſephus Antiq. of the Ieases, lib.</hi> 12. c. 8 ſoli. 14. 8.</note> this is one: that the Iewes on the Sabbath being aſſailed by their enemyes, would ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther make reſiſtance, nor yet ſo much as cloſe vp their caues mouth to defend themſelues, and ſo their liues became a ſpoyle to their enemyes cruelty. So ſuperſtitiouſly obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant were they of the Sabbath, as if God had made it to be a ſnare for them, whenſoeuer the crafty enemy ſhould take that oppertunity to inuade them ſo as in caſe of extreme neceſſity, as to ſaue life, yea a beaſts life, the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was not ſtrictly obligatory; much more in ſpirituall obſeruance, touching Gods worſhip, as the Prieſts ſlaying of beaſts for ſacrifice, and the like. Extreame vacation then was not exacted of the Iewes in their keeping of their Sabbath.</p>
            <p>Againe, we ſhewed before, how the prohibition to the Iewes of kindling a fire, and dreſſing of meate on the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath was peculiar to that Nation, or rather Church, and was a type and ceremony. Nor was it extreame, becauſe they liued in an hot climate, wherein their was no extreame neceſſity of fire for one day, which they were to ſupply: by their ſpirituall fire of holy zeale in a due obſeruation of the Sabbath. Though ſome are of opinion, that this prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition of kindling a fire reached onely to ſuch fires, as were vſed about ſeruile workes, and not about their ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary food. But I will not blowe the coales of this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie in this poynt at this time, hauing ſhewed ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent reaſon already of this reſtraint. Onely this I adde, if it were a burthen, layed vpon the ſhoulders of that Pedago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy of <hi>Moſes:</hi> it was to teach them and vs, to put a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betweene that hard yoake of the Ceremoniall Law. <hi>Acts.</hi> 15.10, and that <hi>ſweete yoake,</hi> and <hi>light bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then</hi>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:7347:29"/> of Chriſt, <hi>Matthew,</hi> 11.30.</p>
            <p>In the next place, where they ſay, that one whole day for the Sabbath, or one ſeauenth day, or one day of ſeauen, was meerely Ceremoniall: I would aske them how the memoriall of the Commandement could bee kept, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a ſpeciall time or day? vnleſſe they will ſay, that the morality, being perpetuall, is not tyed to any one day. But ſeeing the Morall Law cannot be kept by the Church in this world, without time (for as the Preacher ſaith,<note place="margin">Eccle 3.1.</note> 
               <hi>There is a time for euery purpoſe vnder the Sunne</hi>) and this time of kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the fourth Commandement is limited by God to the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> day: how can this day be ſeparated from the Sabbath, as being an inſeparable circumſtance of the ſubſtance of that Commandement? Yea, ſo inſeparable by diuine appoynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as Gods wiſedome did beſt know the Sabbath cannot be ſolemnely kept, vnleſſe it be one of the ſeauen, I ſay not, one fixed day of ſeauen to laſt for euer from the <hi>Creation</hi> to the end of the world without alteration; for ſo it was ceremoniall in the old Teſtament: but the proportion of a ſeauenth part of our time decreed by Gods owne inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and perpetually annexed to the morality. And the Lord who limited a ſeauenth day for reſt, and to bee kept holy, hath noe where left it arbitrary to man, to allow what day or proportion of time liketh him for that purpoſe beyond the number of ſeauen. For as God hath reſerued a tenth of our goods (though we owe him all that we haue) as ſacred to himſelfe, and by meanes whereof hee ſanctifies all the 9 parts to our vſe: ſo alſo a ſeauenth of our time (though- the whole time of our life is to be ſpent to his honour) for the ſanctification of our whole life. And both theſe ſerue ioynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the more commodious, compleate, and ſolemne ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of his worſhip and ſeruice, which alſo redounle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth not onely to our temporall, but ſpirituall and eternall good. Nor is it now in mans power to alter the Lords day into any other ſeauenth day of the weeke, ſith it is Chriſts owne Ordinance, and therefore vndiſpenſable.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:7347:30"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Inuij Praelect:</hi> in Gene 2.2</note>
               <q>The learned <hi>Iunius</hi> on <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.2. concerning the Sabbath thus ſpeaketh: <hi>Haec lex, &amp;c.</hi> This Law (of the Sabbath) is naturall, hauing a ceremoniall deſignation of one day affix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnto it. This ſeauenth day, added of God, is not naturall, but poſitiue. A ſeauenth day is naturall, and remaineth, but the ſeauenth from the creation appoynted of God, is po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitiue, inſtead whereof the Lords day ſucceedeth in the chriſtian Church, called the firſt day of the weeke, and the Lords day, <hi>Reu.</hi> 1.10. celebrated, <hi>Acts.</hi> 20.7. <hi>&amp;.</hi> 1, <hi>Cor,</hi> 16.2. <hi>Cauſa mutationis, &amp;c.</hi> The cauſe of this mutation is Chriſts reſurrection, and the benefit of reſtoring the Church in Chriſt: the commemoration of which benefit ſucceeded the memory of the creation, not by humane tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, but by Chriſts owne obſeruation and inſtitution; who both on the day of his Reſurrection, <hi>Et octauo quoque die,</hi> and on euery eight day, vntill his aſcenſion into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, appeared to his Diſciples, and came into their aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly. And the ſame was done by the conſtant obſeruation of the Apoſtles and Diſciples, and of the Church of Chriſt, to which by the inſtitution and example of Chriſt the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles deliuered the obſeruation of the Lords day which is well ſet forth by <hi>Cyril.</hi> lib. 12. in <hi>Iohan.</hi> cap. 58. by <hi>Auguſtine ad Caſulanum,</hi> Ep. 86. <hi>et ad Ianuarium</hi> Ep. 119. cap. 13. And therefore <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> in his fift ſermon of the Reſurrection writteth, that of old in the Primitiue Church this day was called by three names, The Lords day, The day of bread, and the day of light. The Lords day, becauſe in it, being a ſolemne memoriall of Chriſts reſurrection, they attended to his word and worſhip: the day of bread, becauſe in it the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the Lords ſupper was adminiſtred: and the day of light, becauſe on it was obſerued the adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Baptiſme, For the ancients called Baptiſme <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, illumination and the day of Baptiſme <hi>diem</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the day, of lights; and the Baptized were called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, New illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minates. Wherefore ſith the Lords day by Chriſts Act, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, and inſtitution, by the moſt conſtant obſeruation of the Apoſtles and the auncient Church, and by the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:7347:30"/> of Scripture, hath bene obſerued, and put in the place of the Iewes Sabbath: <hi>ineptè faciunt, &amp;c.</hi> They doe abſurdly, who affirme that the obſeruation of the Lords day contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues in the Church by Traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and not by authority of the holy Scripture, that by theſe helpes they may <hi>(ſi Deo placet)</hi> ſupport the Traditions of men.</q> So he.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, where they ſay, that the generality onely of kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping a Sabbath, was Morall: this generality or morality muſt either now bee quite loſt: or elſe doth neceſſarily import ſome ſpeciall day for chriſtians, wherein ſolemly to keepe this morality (vnleſſe we be bound euery moment or day of our life to keepe it) as well as for the Iewes of old, by Gods owne limitation.</p>
            <p>But fourthly they ſay that the vacation and abſtinence from ſeruile labour, or the ordinary workes of a manes worldly calling, is not any part of the morality of the fourth Commandement, but a meere ceremony, and ſo abrogated. This is a ſtrange Paradox. For then the whole obſeruation of the ſabbath as touching the reaſt of it, was a Ceremony: and where is then the morality of it? ſtands not the mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of it in corporall reſt, and ſpirituall exerciſe? Or elſe tell us wherein? Nay certainely that cannot bee a meere cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, which laſteth for euer. But vacation and reſt from bodily labour laſteth for euer, euen in Heauen, in the keeping of the eternall Sabboth; as the. Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Heb:</hi> 4.9.10. And <hi>Reuel:</hi> 14.13. And in heauen there is noe pleace for meere ceremonies. Therefore vacation from labour on the Sabboth is no meere ceremony, but one ſpeciall part of the moralitie commanded in the Sabbath. So that to reſt from labour is of the very eſſence of the Sabbath, which is therefore called Sabbath or reſt, becauſe one cheife part of the obſeruation of it ſtands in reſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> But they obiect: That the Commandement of the Sabbath is not morall becauſe it bindes not to all times and to euery day, as well as one in the weeke.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Though the externall ſolemne reſt of it binds but for one day in the weeke, yet the due Sanctification of it is
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:7347:31"/> ſuch, as it reatheth to the Sanctification of the whole time of our life, yea to the Sanctifying of our perſons, acſions, affections, &amp;c. by the right vſe of the meanes, as the Word and Prayer. For (as wee ſayd before) as God by reſeruing and conſecrating the tenth of our goods, thereby ſanctifies all the 9 partes vnto vs: So by ſetting apart and hallowing the ſeauenth of our time to his ſeruice, he extendeth ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication to euery day of our life, that therein wee might bee holy. Againe, affirmatiue precepts ceaſſe not to be morall, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they bind not, <hi>ad ſemper, to all times:</hi> it ſufficeth they binde <hi>ſemqer, all wayes,</hi> in their due time and place.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, they deny, that the <hi>Lords day,</hi> the chriſtians Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, hath any relation to the fourth Commandement, of the Sabbath day, as ſucceeding in the place of it. And their reaſon is, becauſe (ſay they) the <hi>Lords day</hi> is not by any Diuine inſtitution, but humane onely, and therefore not of the ſame force with the fourth Commandement. This aſſertion, &amp; reaſon is noe leſſe vnreſonable and peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, then the former. How? The Lords day not of Diuine inſtiutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but humane onely? Eccleſiaſticall they grant, though Apoſtolicall they name not; but in no caſe diuine; that they expreſſely and ſtiffely deny. Firſt therefore wee will proue, that the Lords daye is of diuine inſtitution: Secondly, that it ſucceeds in the place of the Sabbath, and ſo beitng of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine inſtituiton, hath the force of a Commandement. Firſt, that it is of deuine inſtitution, thouigh wee haue no expreſſe Word of Chriſt, yet we haue his Act, &amp; worke for it, Which is euer as good as his word. We ſhewed before, how Gods Act in his reſting in bleſſing and ſanctfying the Sabbath or ſeauenth day, was his inſtitution. For to what end did he bleſſe and ſanctifie it? For, himſelfe? what needed hee? No ſurely for man, for whom the Sabbath day was made to reſt in, as well as the ſixt to labour in. For <hi>the Sabbath was made for man,</hi> ſaith the Lord of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath.</p>
            <p>This inſtitution was in Paradiſe. It ſtands indeede, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.2. before the fall of <hi>Adam.</hi> But if <hi>Adam</hi> fell the ſame
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:7347:31"/> day of his Creation, being the ſixt day, as the beſt Diuines thinke: then it is ſet by way of anticipation, or <hi>Hyſteron Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teron;</hi> and ſo this ſeuenth day began next after the Fall. when the ſon of God incarnate was cleerely promiſed, in which reſpect <hi>the Sonne of man</hi> Chriſt, was <hi>Lord of the ſabbath day</hi> being the Inſtitutor of it, vnder whom Adam began his ſpirituall life in the obſeruation or ſanctification of the Sabbath. And then (I doubt not) he began to Sacrifice, as hee taught his ſonnes afterwards, as wee ſee <hi>Gen.</hi> 4. it being not vnprobable, that thoſe <hi>ſkins,</hi> wherewith God cloathed Adams ſhamefull nakednes, were of the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, which God taught him now vnder Chriſt to offer, as a type of Chriſt cloathing vs with the <hi>robe of his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes</hi> imputed to vs, and merited for vs by the ſacrifice of his death, which ſacrificing ſhall wee deny to bee of <hi>diuine inſtitution,</hi> becauſe wee find it not there expreſſely comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded? Otherwiſe it had beene <hi>will-worſhip,</hi> and ſo abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, whereas <hi>God had reſpect to Abel and to his offering.</hi> And that he reſpected not <hi>Cain,</hi> it was on <hi>Cains</hi> parte for want of faith. <hi>Heb</hi> 11, 4 And why ſhould not man then in the ſtate of inocency haue a Sabbath to reſt ſolemnly in, and to be vacant for Gods worſhip, as hee had a taske (though not toyleſome) layed vpon him to dreſſe the garden, and ſo much the more, being now caſt out, hauing a hard and ſore toyle impoſed on him to till the ground, whence hee muſt eate his bread with ſowre or brackiſh ſauce, to wit, the <hi>ſweat of his face?</hi> Other wiſe, if hee had had no Sabbath to reſt in, his ſtate had bene moſt miſerable, as attended with inceſſant toyle and trauell. And when (in moſt likelyhood) did Cain and Abell bring their ſacrifices? Moſt likely on the Sabbath. For the text ſayth <hi>Mikets iamim</hi> in the <hi>end of the dayes,</hi> which ſome referre to the end of the yeare,<note place="margin">Gene. 4.3.</note> as <hi>Ex.</hi> 22.16. and why not alſo may it be ment of the end of the <hi>weeke dayes?</hi> But I will not contend. Thus Adam no doubt, had the Sabbath, not onely before his fall, written in his heart, but after his fall a ſpeciall day euen the ſeauenth aſſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him vnder Chriſt the Redeemer, <hi>the Lord of the Sabbath</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:7347:32"/> And Gods owne act in reſting from the worke of Creation, and in bleſſing and ſanctifying the Sabbath day for mans vſe and comfort, was warrant enough to make it of diuine inſtitution, without any other expreſſe Commandement. The like wee ſay of the <hi>Lords day.</hi> That which gaue it a ſtampe of diuine inſtitution, was the Lords owne Act in bleſſing and ſanctifying this Lords day with his bleſſed and glorious <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> when now hee ceaſſed from the worke of <hi>Redemption,</hi> a greater and more glorious worke then that of <hi>Creation;</hi> now beginning alſo, and conſecrating the eternall Sabbath. So that this very act of Chriſt was a ſufficient conſecration of this day, as the Sabbath of our Redemption; and therefore iuſtly ſtyled by the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>the Lords day,</hi> becauſe conſecrated not onely to him, but by him as the author of it. Therefore alſo is he rightly intitled <hi>Lord of the Sabbath day</hi> of the Iewes, as alone ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a power to abrogate that, and to initiate this day. For in like manner the Sabbath is called Gods owne <hi>Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, (Iſay.</hi> 58.) and <hi>the Sabbath of the Lord our God, (Exod.</hi> 20.) which hath relation to Chriſt the Redeemer. <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.2. to ſhew, that hee is the <hi>Lord,</hi> and inſtitutor of it. So that it belonged to him alone to cancell the old, and to conſecrate a new Sabbath to Chriſtians, in memoriall of a better Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and as the entrance &amp; iniatition to the eternall Sabbath. Againe, obſerue how he honours this day. For the very day of his Reſurrection, his Diſciples being aſſembled, hee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents himſelfe perſonally vnto them, comforting and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming them with the ſenſible euidence of his Reſurrection, and breathing on them the gifts of the Holy Ghoſt. And, becauſe they ſhould take ſpeciall notice further of this day, iuſt eight dayes after, when this day came about againe, hee appeared to them the ſecond time where they were aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and ſtanding in the midſt of them, as Lord of his Church, ſalutes them with his <hi>peace,</hi> and ſhewes them ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſignes for the fuller confirmation of his Reſurrection. And yet for the more abundant confirmation of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration of this day, after his Aſcention hee ſends the Holy
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:7347:32"/> Ghoſt on this very day 50 dayes after his Reſurrection, whoſe powerfull preſence was an euident ſanctification of this day by his manifold giftes &amp; graces to his Church vnto the end of the world. And, it is ſpecially to be noted, that on thoſe dayes, wherein Chriſt appeared to his Diſciples, and the Holy Ghoſt deſcended, they were all aſſembled ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly together in a holy communion in prayer, and other ſacred duties: So that Chriſts twice appearing vnto, and the Holy Ghoſt deſcending viſibly vpon his Diſciples when they were aſſembled, and all vpon this day, was warrant ſufficient for the Apoſtles, and ſo for the ſucceeding Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, to continue the ſanctification of this firſt day of the weeke by their holy aſſemblies, and exerciſes, as <hi>Prayer, Preaching, adminiſtring the Sacraments, Almes</hi> &amp;c. They ſaw, that this was the ſpeciall day ſelected and ſealed by Chriſt, and the Holy Ghoſt (<hi>For in the mouth of</hi> 2. or 3. <hi>witneſſes ſhall euery word be eſtabliſhed</hi>) for publique ſacred aſſemblies, wherein they might expect Chriſts preſence, by his ſpirits influence, in ſanctifying his people in their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exerciſes on that day. Herevpon it grew a perpetuall Ordinance, not firſt conſtituted by Apoſtolicke authority, but ſeconded and followed by them in their practize, as <hi>Acts.</hi> 20.7. and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.2 vpon which place Maſter <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins</hi> iudiciouſly obſerueth, that <hi>Paul commanded nothing as an ordinance to bee obſerued by the Church, but what hee had from Chriſt. But to make collection for the poore euery Lords day, or firſt day of the weeke,</hi> as a conſequent or concomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant fruite of other Sabbath-duties, as <hi>Preaching, Prayer, Sacraments,</hi> was (ſayth he) <hi>a conſtitution Apoſtolicke, and ſo of diuine authority;</hi> and therefore no meere humane inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And wee ſay, that the ground and cauſe hereof was Chriſts <hi>Reſurrection.</hi> So as it is a groſſe <hi>Solecime</hi> in Diuinity to admit an <hi>Inſtitution</hi> to be <hi>Apoſtolicke,</hi> &amp; yet to denie it to be of diuine authority. Thus <hi>the firſt day of the weeke, the Lords day</hi> grew to be the day of holy aſſemblies for Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, from that <hi>firſt day of the weeke,</hi> wherein Chriſt roſe againe, and appeared to his Diſciples, as wee haue touched.
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:7347:33"/> And from this ſpring did the auncient Fathers deriue the ſanctification of this day, as by ſo many continued ſtreames of ſucceſſion. Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſayth, <hi>Dies Dominicus, &amp;c. The Lords day was not to the Iewes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug: <hi>Ianuario</hi> Epis. 119. c 13.</note> 
               <hi>but to Chriſtians declared by Chriſts Reſurrection, and from that began to bee kept holy.</hi> And elſewhere <hi>Proepenitur dies Dominicus Sabbato, &amp;c. The Lords day is preferred before the Sabbath, by the fayth of the Reſurrection,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. Ca ſulano Preſbytero Ep. <hi>86.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>not by the faſhion of refection, or licentiouſnes of drunken mirth.</hi> And againe, <hi>Domini Reſurrectio, &amp;c. The Lords reſurrection hath promiſed us an eternall day, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated to vs the Lords day;</hi> And <hi>Ambros, Dominica nobis &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">De verbis Apoſt ſer: <hi>15-</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>To vs the Lords day is ſo honourable and ſacred, becauſe in it the Sauiour, as the ſun ariſing, diſpelling infernall dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, hath ſhined forth in the light of his reſurrection. And for this cauſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ambros: ſer: <hi>61:</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>this day of the men of the world is called Sunday, becauſe Chriſt the Sunne of righteouſneſſe ariſing, did enlighten it.</hi> But what neede we ſeeke a <hi>cloud of witneſſes,</hi> of men, when we haue diuine <hi>Sarrs</hi> in Scriptures (though ſhining in a darke place, till the day did dawne) which may giue vs ſufficient light to direct vs to this day? For firſt it is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent that the ſeauenth day which was commanded the Iſraelites of the old Teſtament to celebrate for the Sabbath, was giuen them in memoriall of their deliuerance from the Egyptian bondage, as we noted before out of <hi>Deu.</hi> 5, 15, And thus it was ceremoniall and ſubiect to be changed into another day, to wit, <hi>the Lords day,</hi> which ſhould ſucceede in memoriall of our <hi>Redemption</hi> and deliuerance from our ſpirituall bondage, whereof that corporall was a type, which Redemption and deliuerance was finiſhed in Chriſts Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection; and therefore who ſhould haue power, but Chriſt, <hi>the Lord of the Sabbath,</hi> to change the Sabbath into the Lords day?</p>
            <p>Againe, another remarkeable place we finde in <hi>Leu.</hi> 23.10, &amp;c. where the <hi>ſheafe of the firſt fruits</hi> was to bee waued by the Prieſt before the Lord the day after the Sabbath. This <hi>ſheafe of the fruits</hi> was a pregnant type of Chriſts riſing againe,<note place="margin">2 Cor: 15, 20. Leui: 23.11.</note> the <hi>firſt fruits from the dead.</hi> This ſheafe
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:7347:33"/> was to bee waued the next day after the Sabbath, and not elſe. This was fulfilled in Chriſts reſurrection, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch was the day after the Sabbath, and becauſe this Sabbath was chiefely ment of the Paſſeouer, which was a high Sabbath, to be ſure, it was a double Sabbath, (the Sabbath of the Paſſeouer concurring together) wherein Chriſt reſted in the graue. The very next morning was <hi>Chriſt, the firſt fruites, waued</hi> before the Lord, when in the Earthquake hee roſe from the dead <hi>the firſt fruites of them that ſleepe.</hi> This was <hi>the ſheafe of the firſt fruites,</hi> which was <hi>accepted</hi> for vs,<note place="margin">Rom: 4, 25 Rom: 11.19.</note> 
               <hi>for he roſe againe for our iuſtification?</hi> And <hi>if the firſt fruites be holy, the lumpe is alſo holy.</hi> And the meate offring of this day was twice as much, as vpon any other day, euen <hi>two tenth deales;</hi> whereas the reſt had but one, which is a matter worthy of heedefull obſeruation. This typed and ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed ſome thing extraordinary as touching this dayes oblation. And the offering was made <hi>by fire vnto the Lord for a ſauour of Reſt,</hi> as the Hebrew hath it. This pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figured the <hi>Reſt</hi> of this day of the ſheafe of firſt fruites, of Chriſts reſurrection. And this reſt had relation not onely to Chriſt, who now had finiſhed the worke of Redemption: but alſo to all the Redeemed. For from this very day of the ſheafe of firſt fruites, they were (Leuit. 23.15.16.) to reckon 7 <hi>Sabbaths or weekes compleate,</hi> which incluſiuely containeth 50 dayes, and ſo the ſeauenth firſt day of the weeke next af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Sabbath, they muſt offer a new meate offering vnto the Lord. This was the feaſt of Pentecoſt, which being fully come (<hi>Act.</hi> 2.) the Holy Ghoſt came downe viſibly vpon the Church, ſo fulfilling that typicall propheſie,<note n="*" place="margin">Leuit. 23.17:</note> or Propheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call type. And this meate offring of loaues, and the like, being called alſo a <hi>firſt fruites vnto the Lord,</hi> ſignifyed and prefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gured that <hi>Firſt fruits</hi> of the Church of the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, offered, conſecrated, and ſanctified vnto God that very day, wherein the Holy Ghoſt deſcended. For behold two <hi>waue loaues,</hi> moulded vp of ſo many graines, the one of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> the other of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> both one offering,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:7347:34"/> being a collection of all the Nations vnder Heauen, euen the Catholike Church repreſentatiue, were the <hi>firſt fruites vnto God, and vnto the Lambe,</hi> ſanctified in Chriſt the <hi>firſt fruites.</hi> Theſe are thoſe waue-loaues,<note place="margin">Iſychius Praeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byt, Hirroſol. in Leuit <hi>23,</hi> Planius ergo Legiſlator ſuam demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtran volens men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ab altero die Sabbati nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rari praecipit <hi>50</hi> dies, Dominicum Diem procul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dubio volens in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligi. Hic enim eſt altera Dies Sabbati.</note> that are <hi>holy to the Lord, for Chriſt eur High Prieſt: Leuit.</hi> 23.20. and this offering be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came <hi>a ſauour of reſt, v.</hi> 18. as wee ſhewed <hi>v.</hi> 13. no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſtill the reſt of this day. So as this ſelfe ſame day is ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnely proclaimed to bee <hi>an holy Conuocation;</hi> Therein no ſeruile worke is to bee done: &amp; this to ſtand as a ſtatute vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repealable. Hereupon <hi>Iſychius</hi> ſaith: <hi>Therefore the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuer willing more plainely to expreſſe his minde, commanded them to reckon from the next day of the Sabbath</hi> 50 <hi>dayes, thereby willing without doubt the Lords day to be vnderſtood. For this is that next day after the Sabbath. For which cauſe</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>the Holy Ghoſt came not downe in any other day of the weeke, but in that day of the Reſurrection, wherein the ſheafe of firſt-fruits was waued before the Lord.</hi> Thus we ſee how the day of Chriſts Reſurrection, is made ſolemne and ſacred not onely by Chriſt himſelfe, but by the Holy Ghoſt ſent downe from heauen, ſanctifying this day for <hi>holy Conuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> or publicke aſſemblies of Gods people for his pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique ſeruice, and this to ſtand as a perpetuall ſtatute to the end of the world; hauing alſo euident and ample teſtimony from the Moſaicall Law, and thoſe Euangelicall types. whence we conclude with M. <hi>Perkins</hi> his argument, in his <hi>Caſes of conſcience,</hi> pag. 113. <hi>That which is prefigured, is preſcribed. But the Lords day was prefigured,</hi> Leuit. 23.10. <hi>therefore it is preſcribed and inſtituted of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A third place wee haue <hi>Pſal,</hi> 118.24: where the Prophet ſpeaking (<hi>v.</hi> 22.23) of Chriſts Reſurrection, he addeth, <hi>This is the day, which the Lord hath made, we will reioyce, and be glad in it.</hi> This is a plane Propheticall inſtitution of this day to bee ſolemnized vnder the new Teſtament. For firſt, <hi>the Lord hath made it,</hi> that is, appointed, and ſet it a part, by marking it out with a glorious worke. And ſecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dly, it is ſo taken of the Church of God, who ſaith, <hi>We will reioyce and be glad in it,</hi> which ſheweth the feſtiuity, &amp; grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:7347:34"/> ſolemnity of <hi>the Lords day.</hi> And although many take this day for the whole time under the Goſpell (as 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.2:) yet none doe exclude or deny the particular acception of it for <hi>the Lords day.</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Ambroſe vnderſtands this to be <hi>the Lords day,</hi> the day of the Lords Reſurrection; <hi>which day</hi> (ſaith hee on <hi>Pſal:</hi> 47, <hi>Titneus) hath its holines from the Lords Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</hi> What ſhall I ſay of Circumciſion, which was limited to the eighth day; loking vpon Chriſts Reſurrection, which was the eighth day; Circumciſion, being a ſinge of that holli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Chriſt brought vnto vs in the day of his Reſurrection, <hi>who roſe againe for</hi> our Iuſtification. But let this ſuffice. Thus hath <hi>the Lords day</hi> not onely reall inſtitution by Chriſt himſelfe, but alſo teſtimony from the <hi>Law and the Prophets.</hi> And thus, as <hi>Hugo</hi> ſaith, <hi>The fathers of the old Teſtament obſerued the ſep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenary number, or the ſeuenth of Dayes, Wekes Moneths: Yeares wee of the New, the octonary number, or the eight day, to wit the Lords day, for the reuerence of the Lords reſurrection, and of the ſending of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> Hugo in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>9.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> But here it is obiected, that <hi>the Lords day</hi> hath noe diuine inſtitution, but meerely an hamane and Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall. For elſe how came it to bee inſtituted by <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine the Great,</hi> who made a Law, and preſcribed limits for the keeping of it? The like alſo did other Emperours, Princes, and States, Councels, and Synods in ſeuerall ages.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is no good argument, that becauſe pious Princes make Lawes for the keeping of the <hi>Lords day,</hi> ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is not of <hi>diuine inſtitution.</hi> For ſo good Princes make Lawes againſt Adultery, &amp;c. Therfore the forbidding of theſe ſinnes is it not of diuine inſtitution? King <hi>Darius</hi> makes a decree, that in euery Nation of his Kingdome <hi>men tremble before the God of Daniell, &amp;c.</hi> therefore is not this Law of diuine inſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: <hi>Thou ſhalt worſbip the Lord thy God, and him onely ſhalt thou ſerue?</hi> And becauſe <hi>Tyberius Caeſar</hi> would haue the Romane Senate paſſe a Decree for the deify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſt, or ranking him among their Gods, therefor Chriſt was not God? whereupon ſayth <hi>Tertullian, Ergo
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:7347:35"/> niſi homini placucurit, Deus non erit Deus: therefore if it doe not pleaſe man, God ſhall not be God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it became Chriſtian Princes, when they ſaw how ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect the Lords day was to bee profaned with all licenciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and how prone carnall men were to leape ouer all the bankes and bounds, which God had ſet to keepe them in: for to helpe to make vp the breaches againe, and to ſtrengthen the diuine ordinance by their humane and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall conſtitutions, as wee ſee our noble Kings of England haue done, by name, our pious King Charles, whoſe raigne hath bene honoured with a religious Law for the better keeping of the Lords day, if lawes were as well kept, as they haue bene wiſely, piouſly, and iuſtly enacted by our Progenitors.</p>
            <p>Yet becauſe, notwithſtanding all Lawes, diuine and humane, this <hi>holy day</hi> of the Lord is for the generality of men little regarded, as not requiring the like ſanctification of vs, which the Sabbath did of the Iewes: let vs further ſhew what a reuerend eſteeme the ancient holy men in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ages had, and what pious rules they gaue, concerning the religious keeping of this day. Wee haue noted ſome of their excellent ſayings a little before: wee will adde a few more. And firſt wee obſerue, that they euer did vſe to call the Lords day, by the name of the Sabbath, <hi>Obſeruamus ſabbatum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug, Contra A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damantum. c. <hi>15</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>hoc eſt Dominicam, in ſignum nempe aeterni ſabbati: We obſerue the Sabbath, that is the Lords day, for a ſigne of the eternall Sabbath.</hi> The ſame <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his 95 ſermon <hi>de Tempore,</hi> ſayth, <hi>They which in the obſeruation of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, doe not apply themſelues to good works and prayer, which is to ſanctifie the Sabbath, (and ſanctification is where the Holy Ghoſt is) are like to the ſmall flies bred of the mud, which diſquieted the Egyptians.</hi> And elſewhere (vpon thoſe words,<note place="margin">Aug de Conſeuſu Euang. lib: <hi>1. c. 77.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Math.</hi> 24.20) <hi>Pray that your ſlight be not in the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, nor on the Sabbath day,</hi> hee ſayth, <hi>by winter is ſignified the cares of this life, and by the Sabbath gluttony and drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enneſſe; which euil is therefore ſignifyed by the name of Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, becauſe this was, as now it is, the wicked cuſtome of the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:7347:35"/> Iewes on that day to ſwimme in delicacies, while they are ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of the ſpirituall Sabbath, For the Iewes doe ſeruilely obſerue the Sabbath day vnto ryotouſneſſe. and drunkenneſſe. How much better were it for their women to ſpin, then on that day to daunce. And thus while they carnally kept the Sabbath, they knew it not,</hi> ſayth hee. And <hi>Melius tota die foderent, &amp;c. The men were better to digg all that day, then to tread is out in daunces and meaſures,</hi> Againe, <hi>the Sabbath</hi> (to wit, <hi>the Lords day) is more commaunded vs, then the Iewes. They celebrate the Sabbath ſeruilely, but we ſpiritually? And</hi> how <hi>ſpiritualy not in chambering &amp; wantonneſſe, not in gluttony &amp; dru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kenneſſe. For theſe are forbidden Chriſtians any day, much more on the Lords day, For it were better to plough &amp; harrow, to ſpin &amp; card wooll, which in themſelues are lawfull, then to doe thoſe things on the Sabbath or Lords day, which chriſtians ſhould bluſh at, and be aſhamed of to do at any time,</hi> as to dance, to reuell, to heare playes, to goe to masking and mumning, and the like, which are exerciſes fitter for heathen, then chriſtians, for Bacchanalls, then ſuch as celebrate the Lords Feſtiuall. How then is this day of the Lords to be kept? Neyther as the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eratites, Aeriancs, and Aerians, who faſted all the <hi>Lords day</hi> but madly reueld on other feſtiuals. Theſe are extreames and therefore to bee auoyded. How then? As the chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans did in <hi>Iuſtin Martyrs</hi> dayes of old, who ſayth, <hi>Die ſolis, &amp;c. On the Sunday, or Lords day,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iuſtin Martyr Apol. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>are the chriſtians aſſemblies of Citizens and Countrmen, where the writings of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles and Prophets are firſt reade; then when the Reader hath done, the Maſter of the aſſembly the chiefe Miniſter vſeth words of exortation, his inuiting them to the imitation of things honeſt. The richer ſorte, who are willing, do contribute to the reliefe of the poorer, euery man according to his mind and meanes, and the Collecta, or collections are depoſited with the chiefe Miniſter; he therewith ſuccoureth the Orphans and poore &amp;c. This is that day, wherein God created the world, and Chriſt roſe againe from the dead.</hi> So hee. And Saint <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom</hi> vpon the Apoſtles words, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.1, <hi>Behold</hi> (ſayth
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:7347:36"/> he) <hi>How fitly the Apoſtle rayſeth his exhortation from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of this day of the weeke, as being the fitteſt day, wherin to exhort vnto almes; as if the Apoſtle had ſayd, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what things yee haue obtained this day, vnutterable good things, yea the very roote and ſpring of our life ſtands in it. Not that it is a fit day onely for giuing of almes, but that it hath a reſt, and is free from worldly affaires, and the mind being vacant from moleſtations is the apter &amp; more inclinable to mercy, and it brings with it a great efficacy in the vſe of the celeſtiall Ordinances.</hi> And Saint Auguſtine: Omni Die Dominico, &amp;c. <hi>Euery Lords day come to the Church, and ſpend not the day in pleading, and brabbles, and idle chat, but with ſilence hearken to the word of God, and pray for the peace of the Church, and for the pardon of your ſinnes, &amp;c.</hi> And Bernard ſayth. out of <hi>Eſay.</hi> 58.13. <hi>He calleth the Sabbath</hi> (ſayth hee) <hi>not onely a delight, but he addeth, holy and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryous to the Lord. Nor let the Sabbath ſlipt away with ſloth, but in thy Sabbath worke the workes of God.</hi> And in the Syno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal Epiſtle of the ſecond ſynod of Matiſcon, wee haue theſe words: Cuſtodite Diem Dominicum, &amp;c. <hi>Keepe the Lords day, which hath a new brought you forth, and hath freed you from all ſinnes; as being that day wherein Chriſt roſe for our iuſtification. Let none of you bee vacant to miniſter fewell for ſuites in Law, let none plead cauſes, let none draw vpon himſelfe ſuch a neceſſity, as to compell the cattell to beare the yoake.. Be all of you taken vp with hymmes in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of God, being content in minde and body. Let euery one ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten to the next Church, &amp; their humble himſelfe on the Lords day with prayers and teares. Let your eyes and hands be all that day open to God. For that is a perpetual day of reſt, that is made knowne in the law &amp; the Prophets, being inſinuated vnto vs by the ſhadow of the ſeauenth day. Iuſt it is therefore that wee doe vnanimouſly celebrate this day, by which wee are made that which before wee were not. Let vs performe to the Lord a free ſeruice, &amp;c. Not that the Lord requires of vs, that wee ſhould celebrate the Lords day with bodily ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinence;
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:7347:36"/> but hee requireth our obedience, by which, tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pling all terrene actions vnder our feete, hee may mercifully lift vs vp euen vnto Heauen. If therefore any of you ſhall ſlight or contemne this our wholeſome exhortation, let him know that for the quality of his demerit hee ſhall bee puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed of the Lord, and henceforth implacably vnder the ſacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotall indignation. If hee bee a Lawyer, hee ſhall bee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſed of his pleading without recouery; if a Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man or ſeruant, hee ſhall bee ſore beaten with clubs: if a Clearke, or ſo, hee ſhall bee ſuſpended ſix months from his Fraternity, &amp;c.</hi> And in the Councell of Dingelfing <hi>On the Lords day let men bee vacant for diuine reſt, and abſtayne from worldly and profane buſineſſe. Hee that this day ſhall doe any worke about the Cart, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, let his oxen bee confiſcate. If he ſhall proceed on obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately, let him be made a bondſlaue. And Charles the great in his conſtitutions forbiddeth markets to be kept any where on the Lords day; nor any ſeruile workes to be done therein.</hi> We might bee infinite in ſuch like inſtances of pious conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for the ſolemne and ſacred keeping of the Lords day; but let theſe ſuffice by the way.</p>
            <p>Onely one thing remaines to bee reſolued, whether the fourth Commandement reach vnto ſeruants, as well as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Maſters of Families, ſome would reſtraine the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement onely to Maſters excluding ſeruants thus farr, that in caſe a Maſter command his ſeruant any ſervill worke on the Sabbath, or Lords day, the ſeruant therein obeying his Maſter, is not anſwerable to God, as a trangreſſour of Gods Commandement, but his Maſter onely is in the tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for ſo commanding. This is a ſtrange piece of Logicke: A Maſter in commanding his ſeruant tranſgreſſeth Gods Commandement: and yet the ſeruant obeying his Maſter therein, tranſgreſſeth not. Doth not the caſe hold a like in other relations, as betweene Prince and ſubiect, ſpirituall Paſtours and People? yes ſay they. But how? Thus: God
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:7347:37"/> (ſay they) hath commanded all men to honour their Parents, &amp; the Parents of their Country ſtands in the firſt, ranke-True who denies it? But what followes there vpon? This, ſay they: <q>The Sonne of God hath commanded all Chriſtians to heare the Church, and vnder forfeiture of communion of Saints; but they that deny the Canons of the Church, or E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict of the Prince, heare not the one, honour not the other: therefore they that tranſgreſſe eyther of theſe Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, tranſgreſſe alſo conſequently, though not immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the commandements of God, yet neyther of both are tranſgreſſed by ſeruants, if they worke by their Maſters commiſſion, and not of their owne electon; for neyther doth the one Law, or the other, neyther the Canons of the Church, nor Edicts of Princes giue liberty and warrant to ſeruants to bee rebellious to their Maſters touching poynt of ſeruice that day, more then others.</q> To this purpoſe they argue, that deny the keeping of the <hi>Lords day</hi> to haue any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance vpon the morality of the fourth Commandement. Here be prege reaſons, which would not lightly be paſſed ouer. Therefore a little to examine the mettle of theſe mens reaſons: firſt we muſt remember, that not only on the Lords day; ſeruants obying their Maſters, in deoing ſeruile worke therein, are guiltles (for ſo they haue euation for it, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying the Lords day to bee of diuine inſtitution, and reſt therein to be any morall duty) but they deny alſo, that the fourth Commandement did binde any Iewes, but onely Maſters of familyes, and not thoſe vnder them. For (ſay they) the Commandement was giuen onely to maſters, and not to ſeruants ſtanding in relation to their maſters, in caſe they ſhould impuſote any ſeruile labour vpon them. It is true the Commandement was giuen principally and immediately to maſters, that not onely themſelues ſhould keepe it, but they ſhould looke their whole family kept it. Yet in caſe the Maſter ſhould neglect his duty herein, and inſtead of commanding his family to keepe the Sabbath, ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyne them ſeruile worke: doth not the Commandement take hold of the ſeruant? What? Is the ſeruant an Aſſe, or
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:7347:37"/> ſott, to yeald blinde obedience to his maſter commanding againſt God? Or is he ſuch a ſlaue, as hee hath not a ſoule to anſwere for to God, as well as his maſter? Or being his Maſters ſeruant, is hee thereby, exempted from being Gods ſeruant? ſayth not the Apoſtle, <hi>Hee that is called in the Lord being a ſeruant, is the Lords freeman? Likewiſe alſo hee that it called being free, is Chriſts ſeruant?</hi> Indeede the Maſters ſin is double, not onely in permitting, and communing but compelling, or commanding his ſeruant to worke, when God commands to reſt: but yet the ſeruant obeying his maſter herein vniuſtly commanding, committes a ſingle ſin at leaſt againſt God, if not alſo double, while he preferreth his earthly, maſters Commandement, before his heauenly maſters. But this (ſay they) is <hi>Petitio Principij,</hi> if Gods Commandement reach not to ſeruants. But we ſhew it doth, if ſeruants be not vnreaſonable beaſts, or blinde Aſſes. Nor ought the Maſters Commandement to bee of force, yea it hath a meere nullity, if it bee contrary to Gods expreſſe Commandement. So that in ſuch a caſe for a ſeruant to obey his Maſter, is againſt and aboue God to ſet vp an Idoll, which is nothing in the world, and ſuch ſeruants ſlauiſhly obſeruing <hi>Sabbatum Aſinorum</hi> the Sabbath of Aſſes, do iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſerue the whip for the Aſſes backe: or that cenſure forementioned in the ſecond ſynod of <hi>Matiſcon, If a ſeruant or ruſticke doe breake the Sabbath, let him be ſoundly dry baſted with clubs.</hi> But (ſay they) the ſonne of God hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded all chriſtians to heare the Church, not to deſpiſe hir <hi>Canons,</hi> or Princes <hi>Edicts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>True. But is Chriſts command abſolute, and without limitation, namely to obey Superiours actiuely, whatſoeuer they command right or wrong, for or againſt God? what if the Canons of the Church doe by mans Traditions diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anull the Commandement of God, as of old the Iewiſh Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue, and of latter times the Romiſh? Are ſuch Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons to be obeyed againſt Gods expreſſe Commandement? If the <hi>Phariſees</hi> and chiefe Prieſts make a Canon to puniſh with Excommunication, or Suſpention, thoſe that ſhall confeſſe Chriſt, or profeſſe or preach his truth and fayth
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:7347:38"/> frely &amp; faithfully: is it not diſobedience to God herein to obey them, and through ſlauiſh feare rather to renounce Chriſt, then not ſubmit to ſuch wicked Canons.</p>
            <p>The Iewes Corban freed Children fom honouring their Parents: and doe not they as well make voyd Gods Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, who in binding ſeruants to obey their maſters commanding againſt Gods Commandement, doe thereby free them from Gods Commandement? And for Princes Edicts we all reuerence, and willingly imbrace and obey them. But without limitation? what if they command againſt God? what if they ſhall forbid by publicke Edict the free preaching of the word of God in any part of it, as ſuch and ſuch points of fayth and ſaluation not to bee handled, ſuch and ſuch hereſies not to bee medled with by way of confutation? Are we not to anſwere in ſuch a caſe, as the Apoſtle did, <hi>Whether it be meete in the ſight of God to obey you, rather than God, iudge you; for we cannot but ſpeake the thinges wbich we haue ſeene and heard?</hi> And <hi>Peter</hi> tels the Rulers boldly and plainely, <hi>Wee ought rather to obey God, then men.</hi> What? becauſe <hi>Nebuchadnezzer</hi> erected his Image, and commanded all to worſhip it, and forbad to pray to any God, but to the King onely, for thirty dayes: muſt this Edict therefore bee obeyed? Noe ſurely. And why? Becauſe it was againſt God; and therefore it ought to haue beene of no force to exact obedience of any. But what (will you ſay?) Muſt we be rebels, in diſobeying our ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours? No, it is one thing not obey, &amp; another to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious; ſuperiours ought not to bee obeyed, if they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand againſt God; Yet this is no rebellion, where men are ready to yeald paſſiue obedience to their vniuſt cruelty, by not reſiſting it, though they derect and deny actiue obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to their vniuſt commands. Thus <hi>Daniel,</hi> thus the three Children did; the one deſires rather to bee caſt into the Lyons denne, the other into the hott fiery fornace, then to diſhonour God, by bowing to the Kings Image. Thus all Gods true bred children haue, and will doe; they
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:7347:38"/> neyther dare obey vniuſt command contrary to Gods word, and a good conſcience; nor yet rebelliouſly reſiſt vniuſt pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments; in both which they obey God.</p>
            <p>But enough of this poynt, at leaſt in this place, where we haue as it were by the way occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally met with it, not purpoſely minded throughly to handle it, but onely as a branch of that morality of the Law of God, the whole bulke and body whereof is hewed at by the Antinomians, to cut it downe by the very rootes.</p>
            <p>Onely let vs adde here a few reaſons and motiues,<note place="margin">Reaſons why the Lords day is to bee ſanct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</note> the more to ſtrengthen, and prouoke vs to the more diligent obſeruation of this great holy day of the Lord. One rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon may bee taken from the compariſon betweene chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans vnder the new Teſtament, and the Iewes vnder the Old.</p>
            <p>How exactly were the Iewes bound to keepe the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, as a memoriall of their deliuerance from <hi>Egypt,</hi> in token of their perpetuall thankefulneſſe? How much more then are we thus bound to ſanctifie the Lords day, in a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall thankefull remembrance of our ſpirituall deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from the bondage of ſin, ſathan, and hell, ouer which Chriſt triumphed manifeſtly in the day of his Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Secondly,<note place="margin">Exod: 31.16.17.</note> as the Sabbath day was giuen to the Iewes as a ſigne and meanes of their ſanctification. So the Lords day in the due ſanctifying of it in the vſe of the meanes is a pregnant occaſion of our ſanctification, and that not only in regard of the ſame Ordinances attending vpon it, but as it is a perpetuall memoriall of Chriſts Reſurrection and in the faith and fact whereof is begun here not onely our ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, but alſo our glorification and eternall Sabbath.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> But if the <hi>Eternall Sabbath</hi> began in <hi>Chriſts Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection,</hi> then what further vſe is there of a ſeauenth day weekely to keepe Sabbath in? Euery day now, yea our whole life time is a Sabbath vnto vs; therefore to keepe a ſeauenth day ſtill, is againſt the nature of the eternall Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:7347:39"/> hath begun in Chriſts Reſurrection. And thus to keepe a ſeauenth ſtill is to goe backe to the Iewiſh ceremony againe, which is aboliſhed in Chriſts Reſurrection.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Though the <hi>Eternall Sabbath</hi> began in Chriſts Reſurrection, and is now eternally kept of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and of the <hi>Church triumphant:</hi> yet during the time of this life, which is meaſured by times and dayes, and in regard of the many corporall neceſſitys of it muſt bee maintained by the labours of euery mans particular calling in which regard the externall condition of chriſtians differeth not from that of Gods people in the former Teſtament: our ſolemne keeping of the Sabbath is no leſſe limited to certaine circumſtances of time, as one day of ſeauen, then theirs was. Nor is this a complying with Iewiſh ceremonies againe. For their Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath was in part typicall: but ours is now the true eternall Sabbath, kept of chriſtians according to Chriſts owne Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, attempering it to the condition of our preſent ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, who muſt as well worke for the good of our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,<note place="margin">Exod: 31.13.7.</note> as ſolemnely reſt for our ſoules good. And therefore Chriſts wiſedome, being the ſame with his Fathers and his owne in the firſt inſtitution of a ſeauenth day keeps ſtill the ſame proportion, not altering the Commandement which ſayth, <hi>Six dayes ſhalt thou labour,</hi> Only he hath altered the day becauſe the typicall Sabbath muſt giue place to the true and eternall Sabbath which we now ſolemnly keepe on the firſt day, of the weeke, as it were the firſt fruites of our eternall Sabbatiſme, in heauen with Chriſt, though our whole life otherwiſe is the true Sabbatiſme begun.</p>
            <p>Againe it is the market day of our ſoules, wherein wee come to Gods houſe the market place,<note place="margin">Eſay 55.2:</note> to buy the <hi>Wine</hi> and <hi>Milke</hi> of the word <hi>without money, or money worth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How is that? By hearing and harekning to Gods word, that truth whereby wee are ſanctified, <hi>Iohn.</hi> 17.17. and to pray vnto him; thus by the <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Prayer</hi> weare <hi>ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay. 55.32:</note> 
               <hi>Harken diligently to me, and eate that which is good, and let your ſoule delight it ſelfe in fatnes; Incline your eares, and
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:7347:39"/> come vnto me, &amp; heare, &amp; your ſoule ſhall liue, &amp; I will make an euerlaſting couenant with you, euen the ſure mercies of Dauid.</hi> Loe, the ſanctifying of the Sabbath, or Lords day in a diligent vſe of Gods Ordinances, is the meanes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the mercies of <hi>Dauid</hi> are made ſure vnto vs. And it is remarkeable, how the Holy Ghoſt doth poynt out Chriſts Reſurrection, by alledging and applying this place of the Prophet, <hi>Act.</hi> 13.34. as thereby not obſcurely inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ſanctification of the day of the Lords reſurrection by a diligent harkning to the word of God, and reuerend v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vſing of other diuine Ordinances &amp; duties of that day. And were it not, that the Lords day did ſucceede in place of the Sabbath, the Sabbath day of the Iewes being aboliſhed: what time for the meanes of our ſanctification &amp; ſaluation were left vnto vs? were it not for the Lords day, we ſhould bee in a far worſe caſe, then the Iewes of old, as being left without opportunity &amp; meanes of ſanctification, all which the Lords day miniſtreth vnto vs; without this, wee ſhould haue no market day for our ſpirituall prouiſion, &amp; merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize of our ſoules, wherein to buy the <hi>pearle</hi> of the <hi>kingdome,</hi> and to ſupply all our ſpirituall wants. And therefore the not well imploying and improuing our prouidence and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence vpon this market day, doth expoſe vs to that cenſure, <hi>Why ſtand ye idle in the market place all the day long?</hi> Such are they, that eyther idle or trifle out the Lords day imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently, or ſuch as prophane it with carnall pleaſures, as fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting and banketing (a too common abuſe eſpecially among our greater Citizens) alſo reuelling and ryoting, playes and enterludes, idle chat and communication, dicing, carding, &amp; many ſuch vnchriſtianlike prophane paſtimes, which Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians ſhould beware of &amp; avoid all the dayes of the weeke, yea all the dayes of their life, much more on the Lords day, wherein the <hi>foot</hi> of our carnall affections ſhould be <hi>turned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from doing</hi> our <hi>pleaſure on the Lords holy day, calling the Sabbath a delight, the holy of the Lord honourably, honouring him, not doing our owne wayes, nor finding of our own pleaſure, nor ſpeaking our own words.</hi> This is <hi>to delight our ſelues in the Lord, and ſo ſhall he cauſe vs to ride vpon the high places of the Earth, &amp; feede vs with the heritage of Iacob; for the mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:7347:40"/>
            <p>Otherwiſe, if the due ſanctification of this day be neglected, farewell all true chriſtianity. If the ſpirituall prouiſion of this day be not carefully lookt after, and brought in, and locked vp, and fitly diſpoſed and diſtributed for all the weeke, we ſhall with the <hi>Prodigall</hi> bring our ſoules to feed one empty huskes. And for men to heare the word that day, and when they haue done, to goe home, and not ruminate and conferre of it, but to ſpend the reſt of this day in idle, or godleſſe exerciſes: what is this, but as if a man ſhould buy prouiſion at the market to ſerue himſelfe and his family, all the weeke, and goe preſently the ſame day, and calling idle companions together, ſpend and ſquander all vpon them at one ſitting, and ſo come empty home? What ſhall we ſay then of the Papiſts, that allow of their profaine markets this day, and for ſpirituall commodities they haue none, but ſuch as are painted, or giue an empty ſound, as their long La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine <hi>Matiens</hi> and <hi>Maſſes,</hi> whereby they haue quite ſhoulde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out the preaching of the word of God; a faire pretence by long prayers to keep out preaching, that ſcarce Sermons may take place in the forenoone, muchleſſe any at all in the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoone, leaſt there ſhould not bee time enough to make vp a Sabbath for Sathan, which they conſecrate to him in all kind of exorbitances and profuſe carnality; that ſoe they may be vacant for theaters, and dancing as <hi>Aug,</hi> ſpeaks; or for Cards, Tables and reuelings, as <hi>Leo</hi> ſpeakes, which is to keep the Sabbath of the golden Aſſe, as <hi>Aug.</hi> cals it, yea <hi>Sabbatum Satana, Satans Sabbath,</hi> for if it be not lawfull to doe the workes of our calling, which on the ſixe dayes are lawfull: With what warrant can we do thoſe things, which are ſinfull, and therefore on noe day lawfull, as not comming within the compaſſe of any Calling at all? And if wee do any thing, to which wee haue not a lawfull calling, we are out of Gods Protection, according to that <hi>Pſ.</hi> 91.11. who co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mands his Angels to keepe his Saints in all their lawfull wayes: but if men goe aſtray in the by paths of carnall and vnchriſtian courſes, then Gods Angell is as ready with his ſword drawn to cut them off; as <hi>Ex.</hi> 4.24. <hi>Num.</hi> 22.23.</p>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:7347:40"/>
            <p>A third reaſon and motiue to ſtirre vs vp to the more carefull and diligent ſanctification of the Lords day, may bee taken from the evill fruits and conſequents, which we ſee do grow from the neglect thereof. For it is eaſie to obſerue, and it is an obſeruation infallible, that where the greateſt profanation of the Lords day raigneth, there all kinde of iniquity and impiety doth moſt abound among ſuch a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Now where is this profanation greater, then when Prayer, together with the powerfull Miniſtery and prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the word, and adminiſtration of the Sacraments are moſt neglected, and ſcanted? what maruell then, if in ſuch places, where the bankes of the publike Ordinances, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the fruite thereof, to wit priuate familie-duties are wanting an vniuerſall deluge of all licentiouſnes doe not ouerflow al? whereas on the contrary, where the Lords day is moſt duely and dutifully obſerued and ſanctified in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcionable frequenting the holy aſſemblies in publick prayer, hearing the word faythfully preached, the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments duely adminiſtred, and the like: there is not onely a- beautifull face, but a ſound body of religion to bee ſeene. Eſpecially where a good Miniſtry and Magiſtracy are the ioynt pillars of the Corporation. So as from the right ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the Lords day doth ſpring all holynes, and power of religion, where by God is honoured, the commonwealth it ſelfe is made glorious, as being eſtabliſhed and combined with the moſt firme bonds of pure religion, the Crowne and ſecurity of Kings and Kingdomes.</p>
            <p>I might hereunto adde many more motiues, which though they bee neceſſary for theſe licentious times (if as well the remedies could bee indured, as the maladies can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not) yet I forbeare at this time, as not ſo ſutable to this ſhort diſcourſe, wherein I feare already I haue bene too tedious; though occaſioned, if not rather inforced by the inportunate Antinomians, the enemyes of all true piety.</p>
            <p>But to ſhut vp all in a word, let mee here giue the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der one ſummary view of their abſurd and impious Tenets.</p>
            <div type="tenets">
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:7347:41"/>
               <head>Poſitions, that the <hi>Antinomians</hi> and ſuch like <hi>Libertines</hi> and ſectaries hold with their vſuall euaſions and diſtinctions.</head>
               <p>THeſe <hi>Antinomians</hi> teach, that <hi>God ſees no ſin in his iuſtified Children, and though he know ſin to be in them, yet he ſees it not;</hi> thus making God like to a blinde man, who ſeeth not thoſe thinges, which he knoweth. And where wee obiect, God ſees ſin in his iuſtified Children, for hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proues, and corrects them for it: they anſwere, <hi>that parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular congregations conſiſt of a mixed multitude, ſome belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, ſome not, and vpon the vnbelieuers onely are the correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and reproofes, and not on the other.</hi> And when tis obiect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, God ſaw ſin, reproued and corrected it in <hi>Dauid</hi> a belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer in Chriſt, who ſayth <hi>Pſa.</hi> 69.5. <hi>Thou knoweſt my fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and my ſins are not hid from thee:</hi> they anſwere with mayntaining that <hi>the iuſtification of the Saints before Chriſts death, and ſince, is not alike, but becauſe there is great difference in the manifestation, to them before, and vs now: therefore there is a difference in their iuſtifying. God did ſee ſin thorough the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt imputed vnto Dauid, but not through that which was imputed to Paul.</hi> ſo they.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obiect.</hi> But Paul himſelfe prooueth, that the iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all the Saints, both before and ſince Chriſts death, is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like. But this they will not allow of, but ſtill will haue eua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. <hi>Ob.</hi> But he ſees their Sinnes daily, becauſe dayly hee commands them to pray for pardon. To this they anſwere <hi>that that Petition is to be ſayed eyther onely for modeſtie, or elſe for the further manifeſtation of their iuſtification, Ob.</hi> But doth iuſtification aboliſh Sin cleane out of a belieuer? <hi>No, for then we ſhould lye,</hi> 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.8, 10. <hi>Ob.</hi> But do you ſee ſin in you, and doth not God ſee it? <hi>No God ſees it not, for hee lookes vpon vs onely in the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt; in that greene glaſſe all he lookes on in it, is greene.</hi> And to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe they miſapplie many ſpeeches out of <hi>Luther</hi> on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:7347:41"/> and others. <hi>Ob.</hi> But we are indeede perfectly iuſtified, but not perfectly ſanctified in this life: becauſe the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe whereby we are iuſtified is Perfect, inherent in Chriſt, and onely imputed vnto vs; but our ſanctification is from Chriſt, and inherent in vs, not perfect in this life, but ſtill imperfect. For that they anſwere, firſt, <hi>that the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſpeaking of ſanctification, meaneth it in a large ſenſe, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending iuſtification vnder it;</hi> and ſo they will not admit, or very hardly, of that diſtinction betwixt iuſtification, and ſanctification, but iumble them together. And ſecondly they ſay, <hi>that a belieuer, is as perfect here, as euer hee ſhall bee here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, but onely in regard of manifeſtation,</hi> and to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe they alledge this text, <hi>Becauſe as he is, ſo are wee in this world. Ioh.</hi> 4.17.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ob.</hi> But the Scripture euery where excites vs to grow in ſanctification, and the more wee grow therein, the more aſſurance wee haue of our iuſtification. But this they deny, for they will not haue our ſanctification to prooue our iuſtification, but that muſt bee manifeſt vnto vs onely by fayth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ob.</hi> But ought not a belieuer to walke in an holy courſe of life? That word,<note n="*" place="margin">One of the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> writ in a lett<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to an orthodo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Miniſter, It is vayne babling when men are caſt downe to rayſe them by duties, and fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daubing, to bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> men on doeings though duties dyed in the blood of Chriſt Then</hi> Paul was a <hi>bab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bler</hi> in deed a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the <hi>Athenians</hi> called him, who thus <hi>raiſed by duties:</hi> as Heb. 12.12.13.14 Then Peter was a daw who <hi>built by duties,</hi> 2 Pet. 15: to 15 we accordingly teach duties but diſclame <hi>merits,</hi> as Chriſt teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vs Luc: 17.10 he there com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mendeth duties but condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth merits; So wee.</note> 
                  <hi>ought,</hi> they cannot brooke, but they ſay <hi>that he cannot but walke in an holy life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ob.</hi> But what then is the rule of that holy life?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw The matter of the Law,</hi> ſay they, <hi>but not the Law, as it is a Law; for they are not vnder the Law; but vnder grace, and the Law is not giuen to a righteous man</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.9. <hi>The Law of loue onely now ſetteth them a worke to walke in an holy life, for they are free now, not onely from the curſe of the Law but alſo from it, as it is a command, or rule of life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And therefore they ſay, <hi>They muſt bee farre from any thought of diſpleaſing God at all by any thing they faile in; So as they muſt take heede of being caſt downe for any failings.</hi> Flat contrary both to the Apoſtles precept, and to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> practiſe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1, 2.3.4.5. and 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.9, 10, 11.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7347:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Againe: <hi>Neyther</hi> (ſay they) <hi>muſt we thinke of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> God at all in whole, or in part, by any thing at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſet vp a calfe of our owne works to dance abou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> like is their Rhetoricke, whereby they pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> poſe vpon their Simple Diſciples, who are like Reeds eaſily ſhaken with euery wind of nouell doctrines, ſuch as tend to carnall liberty, &amp; to poſſeſſe the ſoule with ſpirituall pride. But the <hi>Scriptures</hi> do not ſo teach vs Chriſt. Read 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.1. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.10. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.22. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.5. o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> which our <hi>pleaſing</hi> of God (there commended) by weldoing, the fruite of a liuely fayth is not meant of pleaſing by way of ſatiſfaction, for ſo Chriſt onely pleaſed God: but of acceptation in and through Chriſt. But if we ſhall once bee poſſeſſed with this conceit, that neyther our Sins <hi>diſpleaſe</hi> God, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> our beſt ſanctified actions do pleaſe him; what ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and falſe fleſh to become eyther as ſenſeleſſe, ſtockes and ſtones, or as ſenſuall beaſtes: putting no difference, not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of good and euill, when (I ſay) wee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>aded, that neyther our beſt actions pleaſe God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> worſt diſpleaſe him? This is right <hi>Stoicall doctrine, to bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> with nothing at all, to repent of nothing, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betweene the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ling of a coc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> and of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which nature it ſelfe abhorr <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o Orat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> condemnes. The ſecond ſuch lik<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> that they hold. And who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſame, they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>me and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> dead fayth.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:7347:43"/>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:7347:43"/>
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:7347:44"/>
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:7347:44"/>
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:7347:45"/>
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:7347:45"/>
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:7347:46"/>
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:7347:46"/>
            <pb n="80" facs="tcp:7347:47"/>
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:7347:47"/>
            <pb n="82" facs="tcp:7347:48"/>
            <pb n="83" facs="tcp:7347:48"/>
            <pb n="84" facs="tcp:7347:49"/>
            <pb n="85" facs="tcp:7347:49"/>
            <pb n="86" facs="tcp:7347:50"/>
            <pb n="87" facs="tcp:7347:50"/>
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:7347:51"/>
            <pb n="89" facs="tcp:7347:51"/>
            <pb n="90" facs="tcp:7347:52"/>
            <pb n="91" facs="tcp:7347:52"/>
            <pb n="92" facs="tcp:7347:53"/>
            <pb n="93" facs="tcp:7347:53"/>
            <pb n="94" facs="tcp:7347:54"/>
            <pb n="95" facs="tcp:7347:54"/>
            <pb n="96" facs="tcp:7347:55"/>
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:7347:55"/>
            <pb n="98" facs="tcp:7347:56"/>
            <pb n="99" facs="tcp:7347:56"/>
            <pb n="100" facs="tcp:7347:57"/>
            <pb n="101" facs="tcp:7347:57"/>
            <pb n="102" facs="tcp:7347:58"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7347:58"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
